索引：06:20 - 喷管是如何工作的
16:00 - 气尖发动机如何工作的
19:55 - 气尖发动机的问题
32:50 - 气尖喷管和钟形喷管的对比
41:30 - 专家们如何评论
51:35 - 气尖发动机的未来
54:00 - 总结
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
I'm in Mississippi, at the Infinity Science Center,
我在密西西比州无限科学中心
just outside of NASA's Stennis Space Center,
就在NASA的斯坦尼斯航天中心外面
and I'm here to check out a rocket engine,
我在这里要讨论一种火箭发动机
but not just any rocket engine;
这不是普通的火箭发动机
there's a very special rocket engine in here that's kind of inside out
这是一个非常特殊的火箭发动机 它具有由内而外的特性
-and promises to be as efficient at sea level as a sea-level engine
希望在海平面上具有海平面发动机一样的高效
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/D4SaofKCYwo
原视频发布日期：20191018
翻译：长五遥三真没鸽
校对：旋火
and as efficient in space as a vacuum-optimized engine.
并且在太空中拥有真空优化型发动机的效率
Welcome to the aerospike.
欢迎来到气尖发动机
And with engineers relentlessly trying to optimize rockets in a world
考虑到现实中工程师们在不懈地努力优化世界上的火箭
where even a 1% improvement is a massive leap,
哪怕只有1％的改进也是一个巨大的飞跃
the aerospike engine seems like a dream come true.
而气尖发动机似乎能让梦想成真
Throughout history, there's actually been a number of aerospikes
纵观历史 实际历史上是有一些气尖发动机的
that have made it really far into development.
并且真的已经开始研发了
But to date, none have ever really flown,
但到目前为止 还没有真正飞行过
let alone been used on an orbital-class rocket.
更不用说在轨道级火箭上使用
If they're so good, why isn't everyone using them,
如果它们是那么好 为什么不是每个人都在用？
or for that fact, why isn't anyone using them?
或者说是 为什么没有人用？
Why aren't these brand-new engines,
为什么这些全新的发动机
like SpaceX's Raptor engine, that are built from the ground up, why aren't they aerospikes?
像SpaceX公司的猛禽的发动机 是从头来设计的 而不使用气尖发动机呢？
So today we're going to look at the history of the aerospike engine, and
所以今天我们要看看气尖发动机的历史
then we're going to look at how nozzles work, including things like overexpansion,
然后我们将看看气尖喷管是如何工作的 包括过度膨胀
underexpansion and expansion ratios.
膨胀不足和膨胀比等等
Then we'll look at the pros and the cons,
然后我们会看看这其中的优缺点
the physical limitations and problems of the aerospike engine.
物理局限性和气尖发动机的其他问题
Then we're gonna compare the aerospike to other traditional rocket engines.
然后我们要去比较气尖发动机和其它传统火箭发动机
But that's not all.
但是 这还不是全部
I actually got some never-before-seen photos and videos of some historical aerospike engines.
我居然得到了一些 以前从未见过的照片和一些历史上出现过的气尖发动机的视频
Then I went out and talked with some people who have actually worked on and engineered aerospikes.
然后我到外面并与一些实际研制过气尖发动机的人交谈
Then we're gonna look at some compelling concepts
接着我们要看一些引人注目的概念
and promising prospects for some future aerospike engines.
以及未来气尖发动机的广泛前景
And hopefully by the end of the video we'll know whether or not
并希望到视频的最后 我们会知道
the holy grail of rockets is just waiting to be utilized
火箭(科学领域)的圣杯是在等待被利用
or if they're just simply not worth it.
还是说 这并不值
So put on your favorite aerospike engine T-shirt,
所以 把你最喜欢的气尖发动机的T恤穿上
grab some popcorn a drink and a notepad,
拿点儿爆米花 拿杯饮料和一个笔记本
'cause this is a really long video and we have a lot to cover.
因为这是一个很长的视频 我们有很多内容要讲
So let's get started.
因此 让我们开始吧
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
起飞
and liftoff!
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
- So those of you that follow me on Twitter have probably been watching this video come to life
- 所以 那些在推特关注我的人 可能一直在看这个视频的制作
and have likely noticed my tone change
并可能已经注意到我的语气变化
from "aerospikes suck" to a little more neutral stance on the subject.
从吔屎啦气尖 到对此有点中立
Does this mean I'm maturing?
这意味着我正在变得成熟吗？
And wow, after literally months of research,
哇 经过几个月的研究
this turned out to be a monster.
这原来是一个怪物
I mean, we ended up going through dozens and dozens of hard-to-find documents
我的意思是 我们最终浏览了许多难以查找的文件
to be able to track down the actual numbers
以便能找到实际的数字
from their sources from some of these original papers back in the '60s.
其中一些原始文件来自于上世纪60年代
And although it took me a while, sorry,
虽然我花了一段时间 对不起
The more I learned, the more I realized just how much more I needed to learn,
学的越多 越觉得自己需要学习
邓宁-克鲁格效应
and the more context I knew would need to be in this video in order to make it more understandable.
也就意味着需要在这个视频中加入更多的背景知识 以使其更容易理解
So in order to make this more digestible,
因此 为了使这更易理解消化
索引：06:20 - 喷管是如何工作的  16:00 - 气尖发动机如何工作的  19:55 - 气尖发动机的问题
32:50 - 气尖喷管和钟形喷管的对比 41:30 - 专家们如何评论 51:35 - 气尖发动机的未来
54:00 - 总结
here's the timestamps of the major topics.
这里的各个主题的时间戳
And I've got the links to those timestamps in the description and, like all my videos,
简介中也有时间戳 与此同时 就像我其他的视频一样
I actually have a full article version up on my website,
我也有一个完整版本的文章在我的网站上
everydayastronaut.com
if you want to be able to search for a certain sections or see some numbers later on.
如果你希望能够寻找一个特定部分或以后再查看一些数字
Again, the link's in the description.
同样 链接位于说明之中
b23.tv/av57059171
After I posted my "Is SpaceX's Raptor engine "the king of rocket engines"
在我发布SpaceX的猛禽是最强火箭发动机吗
youtu.be/Sfc2Jg1gkKA
and "Why SSTOs suck" videos,
以及为啥SSTO不好 这两期视频之后
I got so many people claiming that the real holy grail of rockets is actually the aerospike engine.
就有很多人(回复我)说火箭真正的圣杯实际上是气尖发动机
And you're not wrong.
而这也没错
I mean, an engine that magically, thanks to physics, is inherently more efficient at almost any altitude?
我是指 得益于物理学 一个发动机在任何海拔高度上都能天然地更高效吗
An engine that works as well at sea level as a perfectly-tuned sea level engine bell
在海平面时 其能追上正常的海平面发动机的性能
and still performs just as well in a vacuum as a large vacuum bell?
而在真空中 也能达到大型钟形喷管的发动机的性能 这真的能做到吗
Wow!
哇
Yes, sign me up!
是的 我也想问
Why isn't there more love for aerospikes engine in the aerospace industry?
为什么在航空航天业界中没有人喜欢气尖发动机？
I mean, after all, SpaceX engineers tackled the ultimate challenge
我是指 毕竟 SpaceX公司的工程师解决的终极挑战
by developing a methane-powered full flow staged combustion cycle engine.
是研制全流量补燃循环(全流量分级燃烧循环 FFSCC)的液氧甲烷发动机
If you could solve that crazy engine,
如果能解决这个疯狂的发动机
why didn't they try for an aerospike,
他们为什么不尝试气尖发动机呢？
something that promises some pretty substantial gains and they've already been fully developed?
那肯定会带来一些相当可观的收益 甚至 气尖发动机已经得到了充分的开发？
After all, aerospikes definitely aren't new.
毕竟 气尖发动机绝对不是新的发动机
They actually go all the way back to the '60s,
这实际上可以一直追溯到60年代
when engineers were looking for ways to improve upon some early rocket engines.
当工程师正在寻找各种方法来改善在一些早期的火箭发动机时
Now, keep in mind, the engines at this point in time were relatively primitive,
现在 请记住 在这个时候的发动机是比较原始的
so the promise of an aerospike engine was extra appealing.
这样的话气尖发动机发动机或许会有额外的吸引力
Perhaps the most notable and promising aerospike
也许最引人注目并且最有前途的有为气尖发动机
was an aerospike version of the J-2 engine
是J-2发动机的气尖版本
that powered the second and third stage of the Saturn V.
而J-2发动机为土星五号的二级和三级提供动力
This was called the J-2T,
这台发动机被称为J-2T
and on paper it seemed to be a nice and compact version of the J-2
在图纸上它似乎是J-2的精简版
while offering even greater vacuum efficiency than the standard J-2.
同时在真空中 比基本型的J-2拥有更高的效率
Although it hit the test stand 34 times and had some promising potential,
虽然在试验台试验了34次 并有一定的的前途
it was shelved alongside the Saturn V and any potential upgrade path thereof
它的任何潜在的开发升级路线和土星五号一起被搁置了
once the Space Shuttle program began.
也就是航天飞机计划开始的时候
But it was actually considered for use as the space shuttle's main engine.
但是实际上考虑过将其用作航天飞机的主发动机
But as we know, NASA went with a closed cycle bell nozzled engine, the RS-25.
但是 我们知道 NASA使用了闭式循环钟形喷管发动机 RS-25
Rocketdyne also took spare parts from the J-2 and
洛克达因也采用了J-2的零部件
the simplified J-2S rocket engines and developed a linear aerospike engine
和简化的J-2S火箭发动机来研发新的线性气尖发动机
known as the L-1 linear test bed from 1970 to 1972,
也就是L-1线性(气尖发动机)测试台 在1970至1972年间
and it had 44 tests with 3,113 seconds of operation.
它进行过44次共3113秒的试车
But it would be almost 30 years before the concept would be dusted off again
但是 近30年之后 这个概念才被淘汰
and looked at with any serious consideration,
并且经过了认真的考虑
and this time it was for a space shuttle replacement known as Venture Star.
这一次它是航天飞机的替代者 冒险星 的发动机
The Venture Star was a rocket nerd's ultimate dream rocket,
冒险星 是一个火箭迷的终极梦想火箭
a single stage to orbit, or SSTO, fully reusable space plane
一个单级飞行器 或者说是SSTO 完全重复使用的航天飞机
that was to utilize a linear aerospike engine called the RS-2200,
它使用RS-2200这个线性气尖发动机
千年隼是星球大战 中的宇宙飞船
that not only made it look like the Millennium Falcon,
不仅使它看起来像千年隼
but it also promised nearly the same payload capability to low earth orbit as the space shuttle
而且拥有几乎和航天飞机相同的近地轨道有效载荷能力
it was intended to replace.
而航天飞机就是它要替代的对象
In order to minimize risk, Lockheed Martin began development
为了最大限度地降低风险 洛马公司开始研发
of a suborbital demonstration version of the Venture Star called the X-33.
冒险星 的亚轨道验证版 也就是X-33
which was to use a smaller testbed version of the RS-2200 called the XRS-2200.
它会使用缩小测试版的RS-2200 也就是XRS-2200
It was fully operational and had accumulated 17 tests and about 1600 seconds of test stand operations.
对其进行了全系统试验 累计进行了17次共1600s的试车
But because of the overly ambitious use of super advanced carbon composite tanks,
但由于过于激进地使用超先进的碳纤维复合材料燃料储罐
a few other technologies that had yet to be perfected,
以及其他一些有待完善的技术
and some interesting politics, Lockheed Martin may have bit off more than they could chew.
和一些有趣的政治因素 这超出了洛马的能力范围
The Venture Star program and the X-33,
冒险星计划 和X-33
along with the RS-2200 and xRS-2200 linear aerospike engines, were put on the shelf in 2001.
与RS-2200和XRS-2200线性气尖发动机一起 在2001年下马了
喷管如何工作的
Okay, so what the heck?
好了 那到底咋回事儿？
Is the aerospike just a bad luck engine?
是气尖发动机运气不好？
Being assigned only to programs which were destined to be canceled?
只被分配给注定下马的项目吗？
Why aren't any of these plans being resurrected now with more modern technologies?
为什么现在没有任何计划 使用更现代的技术 将这些东西复活？
Well let's first get into how they work,
那么让我们先了解一下他们的原理
and in order to do so,
既然如此
we should do a quick overview of how and why a traditional bell nozzle works
我们应该快速讲解一下传统的钟形喷管的工作方式和原理
so we know how to compare them against aerospikes.
这样才好让它们与气尖发动机进行比较
I mean, after all, the physics are the same between the aerospike and a bell nozzle.
我是指 毕竟 物理学原理在气尖喷管和钟形喷管之中是相同的
So, let's dive in.
那么 我们开始吧
Rockets work by taking a high pressure gas with molecules traveling in all directions
火箭的工作原理是 (产生)高压气体 其分子向各个方向上传播
and turning that pressure into a high velocity flow in a very specific direction,
并将其压力转换为特定方向上的高速喷流
and if all things are going smoothly,
如果一切进展顺利
the direction of the flow is exactly opposite of the direction that the rocket is pointing.
流动方向是与火箭指向的方向完全相反的
b23.tv/av57059171
As we've talked about in my video about the Raptor engine,
正如在我对猛禽的发动机视频谈到了
the chamber pressure in rocket engines can be unbelievably high.
火箭发动机的室压可达到极高的程度
SpaceX's raptor engine is currently the king of chamber pressure
SpaceX公司的猛禽的发动机是目前室压最高的
at 270 bar and they're aiming for 300 bar.
达到了270bar(27MPa) 而他们的目标是300bar(30MPa)
Just to put into perspective how much pressure that is,
为了理解这个压力到底有多大
that's like putting a BMW 740i sedan,
举个例子 这就像把一辆宝马740I轿车
which weighs nearly two tons,
它重达近两吨
and placing it on something not much bigger than an average sized US Postage stamp.
把它放在一张普通大小的美国邮票上
That's how much pressure is pushing down on every single square inch of the combustion chamber.
这就是在燃烧室的每平方英寸上施加的压力
To convert that pressure, engineers developed something called a converging-diverging nozzle,
为了转换这么大的压力 工程师们开发了一种叫做收敛-扩张喷管
or a de Laval nozzle,
或者叫拉瓦尔喷管
that converts those high-pressure gas molecules traveling in all directions
它可以将那些在各个方向上传播的高压气体分子
to a high-velocity gas moving in one direction.
转换为在一个方向上传播的高速气体
Now we're gonna go to fluid dynamic city here real quick,
现在 我们要简单地看看流体动力学
and not just any old fluid dynamics but some super nutty stuff
是一些比较疯狂的东西
where everything gets backwards and upside down
这里的一切都变得违反常识
as we're going to transition from a subsonic high pressure hot gas
因为我们要从亚音速高压高温气体
into a supersonic lower pressure and cooler gas.
过渡到超音速低压低温气体
So if our combustion chamber was just a tube coming off the injector,
所以 如果我们的燃烧室只是一个从喷注器引出来的管子
we'd end up with some hot gas moving out pretty fast, but not super sonic.
我们最终会排出一些速度很快的高温气体 但不是超音速的
And a fun reminder here about rocket engines and rocket engine efficiency:
在此有趣地提醒你们有关火箭发动机的效率的原理
the faster the exhaust gas is ejected, the better.
排出的废气的速度越快 效率越高
So in order to accelerate a gas moving through a tube,
因此 为了加速气体通过管道(喷管)的速度
we can actually shrink the size of the tube.
我们实际上可以收缩管道的大小
The same amount of mass will pass through this smaller area,
相同数量的质量将通过这个较小的面积
and in order to do so, it needs to speed up.
而为了做到这一点 就需要加速
I think the best example of this is a standard old garden hose.
我觉得这方面最好的例子是一个标准的老式花园(喷水)软管
Turn it on and put your thumb over the end of the hose.
打开它 把你的拇指在软管的末端
Now, ignoring a few potential loses,
现在 忽略一些潜在的损失
the same amount of water will flow through the hose regardless if your thumb is covering the end or not.
不管你的拇指覆盖完全与否 相同质量的水都会流过软管
The only thing that changes is the water has to speed up
唯一的变化就是 (在拇指遮挡的情况下) 水的速度会加快
to move the same volume of water through a smaller hole.
来让相同体积的水通过一个较小的孔
Now remove your thumb and the water slows back down,
现在拿开你的拇指 水会慢下来
but both methods would actually fill a bucket in the same amount of time.
但是这两种方法实际上都会在相同的时间内填满一桶
One will just be a lot more splashy than the other.
只不过一个会比另一个更容易泼溅出去
So the same thing applies with gas passing through a tube.
因此 气体通过喷管这件事也是一样的
We can keep shrinking the tube
我们可以继续使管子收缩
until we get to the point where the gas is traveling at sonic speeds, or at the local speed of sound.
直到气体的速度达到音速 或者说是这种介质中的音速 局部音速
Now, I say local speed of sound because the speed of sound goes up with the square root of temperature,
现在 我说局部音速是因为声音的速度随着温度的平方根上升
and because temperature in rocket engines is really high,
因为火箭发动机内部的温度非常高
the speed of sound at the throat
在喷管喉部的音速
can be five to 10 times faster than that of room temperature at sea level.
可以比在海平面下的室温快5到10倍
Once the exhaust gas is traveling at the speed of sound,
一旦废气以音速流动
we can't actually shrink the tube anymore,
再收缩管子就没有意义了
because here's where things get quite literally backwards.
因为这里的情况是完全相反的
Once a gas is traveling at the speed of sound,
一旦气体达到了音速
if you shrink the tube anymore,
如果再收缩喷管
you simply end up choking flow.
只是减少了流量(而不会再提高速度)
So from this point on,
所以从这个角度上
engineers design the nozzle to be the perfect shape
工程师设计的喷管形状
which will convert thermal energy into kinetic energy.
是为了最大化地将热能转化为动能
So as the walls of the nozzle gets wider,
因此 当喷管的管壁变宽的时候
it actually accelerates the gas,
它实际上加快了气流的速度
and the pressure and temperature will lower.
同时降低了压力和温度
If you keep going with this and you make the nozzle big enough,
如果继续这样下去 让喷管变得足够大
you'll get to the point where the exhaust is actually at the same pressure as the ambient air outside,
会让废气和环境气体的压力达到相同的程度
or in the case of sea level, one bar of pressure.
对于海平面的气压而言 就是1 bar(100Kpa)
It's actually kind of amazing to me that
它令我惊异的是
we can go all the way from hundreds of bar of pressure
实际上我们可以在极短的距离内把室压从几百bar(几十兆帕)
down to less than one bar in such a relatively short distance.
降到不到1bar(100千帕)
And it's also weird to me that,
这一点也让我感到奇怪在于
even though the exhaust gas is moving at unbelievable speeds,
即使废气以难以置信的高速流动
the exhaust pressure can actually get really, really low.
废气压力实际上可以变得非常低
And the lower pressure we can get the exhaust gas,
而且 废气压力越低
the more we'll have converted high pressure into high gas velocity, which is desirable.
压力就越能转化为速度 也就是我们所需要的
But as a rocket climbs in altitude,
但随着火箭高度上升
the ambient air pressure outside of the rocket lowers,
火箭外面的环境气压就会降低
so the pressure at the end of the nozzle becomes higher and higher than the ambient pressure outside of it.
所以在喷管的末端的压力就会变得高于外面的环境压力
You can see a rocket's exhaust plume expanding out in all directions as it ascends into the vacuum of space.
在火箭升向太空的真空这段过程中 你可以看到火箭的尾焰在所有方向上逐渐扩散开来
This is why vacuum optimized nozzles are so freaking big.
这就是为什么真空优化的喷管非常的大
The perfect example of this is SpaceX's Merlin engine,
这样做的很好的例子是SpaceX公司的梅林发动机
which has the same combustion chamber between the sea level version and the vacuum versions.
其中海平面版和真空版之间有着相同的燃烧室
The sea level version with its sea level nozzle is small enough
海平面版的喷管足够小
that SpaceX can fit nine of them inside the 3.7 meter wide Falcon 9.
以至于SpaceX的猎鹰9火箭的3.7m直径箭体可以容纳9个这样的发动机
But the upper stage vacuum engine has only one engine
但上面级真空发动机只有一台
because the vacuum nozzle's bell is about three meters wide.
由于真空发动机的喷管直径就要3米
Just look at how snugly it fits inside the interstage of the Falcon 9.
只需看看它在猎鹰9号的级间段内安装得有多紧
You can tell whether or not a nozzle is optimal for the altitude
你可以通过以下方法判断喷管是否适合海拔高度
by looking at the exhaust coming out of the nozzle.
也就是观察来喷管排出的废气
A nozzle that's perfectly matching the atmospheric pressure
与大气压完美匹配的喷管
will have exhaust shooting out straight in a perfectly expanded plume or a perfect column of flame.
会将废气射成完美膨胀的羽状物 或者说是完美的火焰柱
Now if a nozzle is too small for the altitude it's at,
现在 如果喷管太小而不适合所在的高度
it's called being underexpanded
这就是所谓的欠膨胀
and you can see the exhaust immediately getting wider and wider as soon as it exits the nozzle.
并且你可以看到废气从喷管出来后立即变得越来越宽
If the exhaust is traveling out away from the rocket at all, that's energy literally being spent thrown out the sides.
如果废气远离火箭 那就是把能量从两边丢弃了
You want the exhaust traveling as straight as possible.
你希望排气尽可能直
At sea level, nozzles are virtually always too big and that's called being overexpanded.
在海平面 喷管实际上总是太大 这就是过度膨胀
You can tell when a rocket's nozzle is overexpanded
火箭的喷管过度膨胀的判断方法是
because the exhaust gets squeezed tighter by the ambient air as it exits the nozzle
当废气离开喷管时 其被环境空气挤压得更紧
and it will even form shock waves as pressure grows and expands and compresses again.
它甚至会形成冲击波 因为随着压力的增长 废气会再次膨胀和压缩
These are called mock diamonds or shock diamonds,
这些被称为马赫环
and although they look super cool and super pretty,
虽然他们看起来很好看
they're actually a sign of inefficiency from an overexpanded nozzle.
实际上 这是喷管过度膨胀导致效率低下的迹象
So now you might be thinking,
所以 现在你可能会想
why don't they just use vacuum-optimized nozzles at sea level,
为什么不干脆在海平面上用真空优化的喷管
since rockets only spend their first few seconds at sea level,
因为火箭在海平面上只花了前几秒钟时间
ambient air pressure drops in half by only about 5,000 meters or so,
仅约5000米时 环境气压就下降了差不多一半
and they spend most of their time in the vacuum of space?
之后火箭发动机点火的大部分时间都花在太空的真空当中
Well there's a few reasons, but first remember,
关于这件事 有这么几个原因 但首先要记住
the further away the nozzle exit pressure is from the ambient pressure, the less efficient it is.
喷管出口压力和环境压力差值越大 效率越低
So a sea level engine in a vacuum is inefficient and a vacuum engine at sea level is inefficient,
因此 处于真空状态的海平面发动机效率低下 处于海平面的真空发动机效率低下
but there's actually another, even bigger reason why you can't actually use a vacuum engine at sea level.
但实际上另一个更大的原因是 你不能真的在海平面使用真空发动机
It's because the nozzle would likely break due to something called flow separation.
这是因为喷管可能会因所谓的边界层分离而破裂
This is where the ambient air squeezes in against the flow of the exhaust
也就是环境空气会挤压排气气流
and it actually climbs up into the nozzle,
并实际上延伸到喷管中
and it does that so much that it can create these sudden shock waves
它的作用是如此之大 以至于会突然产生一些冲击波
and sudden pressure spikes called flow separations which will most likely damage the nozzle.
而突然产生的压力峰值被称为边界层分离 这很可能会损坏喷管
A nozzle can really only go down to about 40% overexpanded before you get flow separation.
在发生边界层分离之前 喷管最小只能达到40%左右的过膨胀状态
Well, that is unless you look at the Space Shuttle's main engine, the RS-25,
好吧 除非你看看航天飞机的主发动机 RS-25
which used a unique trick to curl the nozzle walls in ever so slightly,
它使用独特的技巧将喷管壁微微卷曲
which allowed them to get down to about 14% overexpansion without flow separation at sea level.
这使它们在海平面不发生边界层分离的情况下 可降低至约14％的过度膨胀状态
This allowed them to be very, very overexpanded,
这使发动机非常地过度扩张
which made them more efficient throughout the entire 8.5-minute ascent
在整个8.5分钟的上升过程中 发动机都会变得更加高效
since they fired from sea level and they stayed running all the way into orbit.
因为它们是从海平面发射的 所以会保持运行至入轨
And considering how little amount of time is spent at sea level,
考虑到在海平面上花费的时间很少
maximizing nozzle design for the vacuum of space was definitely a good thing.
最大限度地设计真空优化喷管绝对是一件好事
But for some reason it's still really weird to think
但感觉很怪的是
that just regular old air at sea level can be higher pressure and actually squeeze in on rocket exhaust.
在海平面上压力正常的环境气体 压力能更大并挤进火箭尾气
But the pressure at the tip of the nozzle is actually pretty low;
但在喷管的末端处的废气压力实际上是相当低的
it's just moving very, very, very, very, very fast.
它只是移动得非常快
And even if you have a huge vacuum nozzle like the vacuum Merlin 1D,
即使你有一个巨大的真空喷管像真空型梅林1D
it's still too small for the vacuum of space.
对于太空中的真空来说 它仍然太小了
If it were to match the ambient vacuum pressure,
如果要匹配真空的环境压力
the nozzle would need to be infinitely long,
喷管得要无限长
and since that doesn't sound like it'd be very light weight or fit inside of our universe,
因为既然它听起来不那么轻 也可能在宇宙里面装不下
engineers find the happy medium between packaging, mass and performance.
工程师们(只好)在材料 质量和性能之间找到了很好的平衡点
The term for how big the throat of the combustion chamber is compared to the exit of the bell
衡量钟形喷管末端对比燃烧室喉部的相对大小的参数
is known as the expansion ratio.
被称为膨胀比
This is the ratio between the area of the throat vs the area of the nozzle exit.
这个比例就是用钟形喷管末端的面积除以喉部面积得到的
Again, for ease of reference,
同样 为了便于参考
let's look at SpaceX's Merlin engine which has the same chamber and throat diameter,
让我们来看看SpaceX公司的梅林发动机 其具有相同燃烧室和喉部直径
but with different bells.
但有着不同的喷管配置
A sea level Merlin has a nozzle that's 0.91 meters wide
海平面梅林的喷管直径为0.91米
whereas the Merlin Vacuum engine has a 2.89 meter wide nozzle.
而真空型梅林发动机具有2.89米直径的喷管
Since both engines have the same throat of 226mm,
由于这两款发动机都有226毫米直径的相同的喉部
this means the sea level Merlin has an expansion ratio of 16:1
这意味着海平面梅林具有16的膨胀比
while the Merlin Vacuum engine has an expansion ratio of 164:1.
而梅林真空发动机具有164的膨胀比
I think we tend to look at a rocket engine's nozzle and go
我认为我们一看到火箭发动机的喷管会说
"Hey, look at that huge rocket engine!"
嘿 看那个巨大的火箭发动机
when really, we're seeing the most insignificant piece of the engine.
实际上 我们看到的是发动机中最微不足道的部分
As a matter of fact,
事实上
many of the rockets we see on display are missing the actual engines or the turbo pumps
我们看到展览中的许多火箭都缺少实际的发动机或涡轮泵
and they just have dummy mock up nozzles.
它们只有假的模拟喷管
So the next time you hear someone say,
所以 下一次你听到有人说
"Check out these huge engines,"
看看这些巨大的发动机
you can push your glasses up on your nose and say,
你可以将眼镜推到鼻子上 然后说
"The final size of the nozzle has only to do with the expansion ratio of the engine bell",
喷管的最终尺寸仅取决于的发动机钟形喷管的膨胀率
"and it does not necessarily correspond to the output of the engine."
它并不一定对应于发动机的输出
It's kind of like pointing to the wheels of a car and saying "Look at that engine!"
这有点像指着一辆车的车轮 并说 看那个发动机
Because it's just like how the wheels of a car transmits the energy of the engine to the road,
因为就像汽车的车轮将发动机的能量传递到道路上一样
the nozzle converts the energy of the rocket engine into workable thrust.
喷管将火箭发动机的能量转换为可工作的推力
气尖发动机如何工作的
Okay, so you can't really fire a vacuum-optimized engine at sea level.
好了 所以你不能真正在海平面使用真空优化的发动机
and this, really, is where aerospikes come in.
确实 这是气尖发动机的初衷
The idea behind aerospikes is
气尖发动机背后的想法是
you allow the ambient air pressure to actually form the walls containing the flow of the exhaust
你可以让环境空气压力形成实际包含排气流的壁
so it's always in nearly ideal conditions at any altitude.
所以它总是在任何高度接近理想的条件
And not only will you not destroy your engine by lighting it at sea level;
你不仅不会因为在海平面上点火而毁掉你的发动机
it's actually gonna perform pretty darn well.
而且它实际上会工作地相当的好
And again, I know it doesn't really seem like it,
再说一遍 我知道这看起来不像是真的
'cause it's just what we're used to, but at sea level,
这是因为我们已经习惯了 但是在海平面上
there's actually an awful lot of air around us.
其实有非常多的空气在我们身边
And you don't really realize how much force it exerts
你不知道它会给你带来多大的压力
until you remove air from something and you see
直到你把空气从某些东西上移开
how much force the atmosphere can actually apply.
才会发现大气到底能施加多大的力
So with an aerospike, the throat of the combustion chamber, or chambers,
因此 在气尖喷管的情况下 燃烧室的喉部 或燃烧室
aims the exhaust gas at what is essentially just a slice of a traditional bell.
基本上不过是把废气对准到传统钟形喷管的一部分上排出
When the engine is at sea level,
当发动机在海平面
the higher pressure ambient air outside of it pushes the lower pressure exhaust against the wall.
外部的高压空气将低压排气推向喷管壁
So now instead of the ambient air pressure squeezing in on the exhaust
所以现在不是环境气压挤在喷管上
and pushing it away from the nozzle wall,
并将其推离喷管壁
the ambient air pushes the exhaust further into the nozzle wall,
环境空气将排气进一步推入喷管壁
which makes flow separation physically impossible.
这使得边界层分离在物理上变得不可能
As the vehicle climbs in altitude,
当火箭在攀升高度时
the ambient air pressure decreases and so does the pressure on the exhaust flow.
环境气压降低 其对废气的压力也随之下降
This essentially makes the wall that holds the exhaust grow, changing its expansion ratio with altitude.
这实质上使喷管壁增长 随高度改变其膨胀率
So really, the air, or the lack of air, forms the outer wall of aerospikes and,
所以实际上 空气或稀薄的空气 会形成气尖发动机(喷管)的外壁 并且
due to the atmosphere getting thinner and thinner as the rocket's altitude increases,
由于随着火箭高度的增加 大气层变得越来越稀薄
the virtual nozzle actually grows with altitude.
虚拟的喷管实际上随高度而增长
But there's still an expansion ratio for aerospike engines,
但是 气尖发动机的膨胀比仍然很高
and this is based on how long the spike itself is.
这是取决于气尖(发动机前的尖头)本身有多长
The exhaust needs to form against the spike,
排气需要靠着气尖形成
and once the spike's gone,
一旦气尖不见了
the exhaust will expand out beyond it in a vacuum just like a traditional bell.
废气会像传统的钟形喷管一样在真空中向外膨胀
Most aerospike concepts have a flat base at the bottom, or a truncated spike,
大多数气尖发动机的概念的底部都是平的 或者说是截短的尖头
which takes the turbine exhaust and puts it through a heat exchanger,
在这个位置 将涡轮泵的废气通过热交换器排出
and that creates a pressure zone in the wake of the rocket
并在火箭尾部产生压力区
that actually adds a little bit of additional thrust in higher altitudes,
实际上在高空额外地增加了一点推力
further aiding the traits that are advantageous.
进一步增强那些有利的特质
In order to make an aerospike engine,
为了制造一个气尖发动机
you need a differently shaped combustion chamber than a traditional one,
你需要一个不同于传统的燃烧室
or multiple chambers that form the unique shape needed to make an aerospike.
或者多个形成独特形状的燃烧室来制造一个气尖
There's two main types of aerospikes:
主要有两种的气尖发动机
there's the toroidal aerospike and the linear aerospike.
也就是环形气尖和线性气尖
With the toroidal aerospike, the combustion chamber is like a donut kind of,
环形气尖的燃烧室就像一个甜甜圈
and the throat is an opening pointing inwards-ish towards a spike.
喉部是一个向内指向气尖的开口
A linear aerospike has rows of combustion chambers
线性气尖有成排的燃烧室
that all point onto a flatter wedge-shaped ramp and has at least two sides,
所有这些都指向一个更平坦的楔形坡道 并至少具有两个侧面
and the exhaust ends up meeting each other at the tip.
排气最终在顶端彼此相遇
Most rocket concepts that utilize an aerospike engine are single stage to orbit concepts,
利用气尖发动机的大多数火箭都是单级入轨(SSTO)的概念
and that is a rocket that is only one stage
也就是只有单级的火箭
and goes straight from sea level to orbit with no separation events.
它会直接从海平面发射 直到轨道 并不进行分离
youtu.be/Sfc2Jg1gkKA
Now I've already done a video on why SSTOs suck,
我已经制作了一段视频 说明SSTO为何很糟糕
and trust me, they're super cool,
相信我 它们超级酷
like yes I want that and maybe someday we'll have it,
没错 我也期待这些 也许有一天会研制出来
but physics just simply dictates that there's a lot better uses of rockets.
但物理学只是单纯地决定了火箭会有更多更好的用途
After all, if the key is truly reuse,
毕竟 如果关键是真正的复用
not putting the entire vehicle through punishing reentry forces is a good place to start.
不要让整个火箭都再入大气层 这会是一个很好的起点
That's why we're seeing fully reusable concepts like SpaceX's StarShip
这就是为什么我们看到像SpaceX公司的完全可重复使用的概念 Starship
be a huge multistage vehicle.
是一个巨大的多级火箭
But an aerospike is a pretty good way to do a single stage to orbit rocket,
但是 使用气尖发动机是实现火箭单级入轨的一种很好的方法
since you can essentially utilize a vacuum-optimized engine at sea level
因为你基本上可以在海平面使用真空优化的发动机
and not only will it not explode,
它不仅不会爆炸
it'll operate about as well at sea level as a sea level optimized rocket engine.
甚至还和海平面优化的火箭发动机工作得一样好
By the math, here's where a working aerospike can nearly double the payload capacity of an SSTO
通过数学计算 使用气尖发动机可以使SSTO的有效载荷能力几乎翻倍
compared to a good bell nozzle engine,
相对于一个好的传统钟形喷管发动机来说
but more on that later when we'll look at whether
但是稍后我们将进一步探讨
or not an aerospike truly is the best option even for SSTOs.
甚至对于SSTO而言 气尖发动机都不一定是最佳选择
气尖发动机的问题
Okay, so other than SSTOs, in general, if aerospikes are so great,
好吧 除了SSTO 一般来说 如果气尖发动机是如此之好
why isn't it being used on every rocket?
为什么没有在每枚火箭上使用它？
I mean, especially on first stages
我的意思是 特别是在一级
where the vehicle transitions from sea level to vacuum-ish conditions.
在这种情况下 火箭所处的环境会从海平面转换到真空
Well there's two main issues that plague aerospikes:
好吧 有两个主要问题困扰着气尖发动机
weight and heat.
重量和热量
Let's start off with heat
让我们先从热量说起
as it's actually perhaps the biggest issue
因为它实际上可能是最大的问题
and it contributes to less than ideal performance and additional weight.
并且会导致性能不理想 并增加重量
That's right.
没错
Now, despite looking like there's a lot less to cool,
现在 尽管看起来冷却的东西要少得多
an aerospike engine actually has a horrendous time keeping itself cool.
气尖发动机实际上要保持长得可怕的时间来冷却
I mean, after all, a rocket engine is basically just getting exhaust gas
我的意思是 毕竟 火箭发动机基本上只是在排放废气
as hot and high pressure as you can
尽可能的承受高温高压
and eventually make it all move in one direction
并最终使其全部向一个方向移动
without it melting the engine trying to contain and direct it.
而不会熔化试图限制和引导它的发动机
And an engine melting, well, means you no longer have an engine.
而发动机熔化 意味着发动机损坏
And as soon as your rocket no longer has a working engine,
而一旦你的火箭不再有能工作的发动机
it tends to fall right back to Earth in a hurry.
它就会很快掉回地球
(rumbling)
隆隆！(大烟花)
The primary way most liquid-fueled rocket engines cool themselves is
大多数液体火箭发动机冷却自身的主要方式是
through a process known as regenerative cooling.
通过被称为再生冷却的方法来冷却
This is where liquid fuel is actually piped through the walls of the combustion chamber
实际上是液体燃料通过燃烧室壁上的管道
and actually most of the nozzle as well in order to cool them down.
以及喷管壁上的管道 来进行冷却
There's also other tricks that rocket engines can do to keep themselves from melting.
火箭发动机还可以采取其他技巧来防止自身融化
There's film cooling with fuel or exhaust, ablative cooling and even radiative cooling.
用燃料或废气薄膜来冷却 烧蚀冷却乃至辐射冷却
Ablative cooling, like how a heat shield typically works,
烧蚀冷却 是像热盾一样工作的
is where you allow parts to sublimate or ablate, and in doing so, they take heat away with them.
通过部分地升华和烧蚀 来带走热量
A good example of this is the RS-68 engine
这样做的一个很好的例子是RS-68发动机
2019年8月22日 德尔塔IV或者说德尔塔IV中型进行最后一次发射并退役
that powers ULA's Delta IV Heavy and powered the now-retired Delta IV.
它为ULA的重型德尔塔IV和已经退役德尔塔IV提供动力
Although it runs on liquid hydrogen just like the space shuttle,
尽管它像航天飞机一样使用液态氢作为燃料
it's exhaust isn't clear like the space shuttle's main exhaust.
它的废气(尾焰)并不像航天飞机主发动机(RS-25)的废气一样清晰
Instead, it has this orange glow to it.
相反 它有这个橙色的光芒
That's actually from the composite nozzle that uses graphite to ablate away,
这实际上是使用石墨烧蚀的复合材料喷管产生的
which takes the heat away with it.
它带走了热量
This is a little less common in modern liquid-fueled rocket engines,
在现代液体燃料火箭发动机中 这种情况不太常见
and it's of course not a good choice if you plan to reuse your engine
并且如果计划对发动机进行重复使用 那么它就不是一个好选择
since you likely would have burnt through the majority of it during the flight.
因为在飞行期间你可能会烧掉大部分发动机
Film cooling can take a few forms either
薄膜冷却系统需要分几种形式
by injecting additional fuel inside the combustion chamber along the walls to keep those areas cooler,
一种是沿着燃烧室壁向内注入额外的燃料 以保持这些区域的低温
by pumping cooler exhaust down along the nozzle, or both.
另一种是沿着喷管壁向下泵送相对低温的(燃气发生器)废气 或两者兼而有之
b23.tv/av57059171
We've touched on the gas generator exhaust before in my video about raptor engines,
在我有关猛禽发动机的视频中 我们之前讲过燃气发生器的废气
but the exhaust from a gas generator or preburner is relatively cool
但来自燃气发生器的废气 或预燃室的废气相对温度更低
since it needs to be a low enough temperature for the turbine to be able to survive being subject to it.
因为废气需要足够低的温度来驱动涡轮泵 才能让它在这种情况下扛下来
It's just super weird to think that you can take hot exhaust, like 1,000 celsius,
想想 能承受1000摄氏度之类的高温废气什么的 真是太奇怪了
mix it with hotter exhaust gas, like around 2,500 celsisus,
然后让它和更热的 大约2500摄氏度的废气混合
and it'll actually end up being somewhere between the two temperatures.
实际上最终会是两个温度之间的某个值
My dumb brain tends to think that if you add those two together,
我愚蠢的大脑倾向于认为 如果你把这两个加在一起
it's the sum of those two numbers and not the average.
它的这两个数字的总和 而不是平均
I guess it's a good thing that I'm not a rocket engineer.
幸亏我不是一个火箭工程师
But hey, I guess I'm proof that it's never too late to start learning thermodynamics.
但是 嘿 我想我证明了 任何时候开始学习热力学都不算太晚
涡轮泵废气歧管
主燃烧室废气
富燃 // 冷的涡轮泵废气
This cooler exhaust gas helps the nozzle, or usually the nozzle extension,
这种较冷的废气帮助喷管 或者通常是喷管延伸部
be in contact with a cooler gas than if it were in contact with the main combustion chamber exhaust.
来接触较冷的气体 这个较冷 是相对于主燃烧室废气来说的
You can see this utilized on the F-1 engine that powered the Saturn V as well as the Merlin 1D Vacuum engine.
你可以看到它在土星五号的发动机F-1和梅林1D真空发动机上的应用
And looking at the Merlin 1D vacuum,
而仔细看看梅林1D真空发动机
you can see streaks in its niobium alloy nozzle
你可以看到它的铌合金喷管条纹
which is radiatively cooled
这就是辐射冷却
but also takes the gas generator exhaust and uses it to cool the nozzle.
但是也使用了燃气发生器的废气用来冷却喷管
多重结构鳍片
The streaks are from little fins inside the exhaust manifold that maintain the structure.
这些条纹来自排气歧管内保持结构的小鳍片
Side note, I used to think these streaks were from the pintle injector, but come to find out,
顺便说下 我曾经认为这些条纹来自针状喷注器 但后来发现了
it's from the exhaust manifold's support braces interacting with the film cooling.
它来自废气歧管支撑支架 与薄膜冷却相互作用
The other way to keep the walls of the combustion chamber and nozzle cool
另一种保持燃烧室和喷管壁冷却的方式
is by having additional fuel injectors along the perimeter of your injector plate.
是在喷注器板的边缘上加上额外的喷注器
The injector plate is generally the entire top of the combustion chamber
喷注器板通常在整个燃烧室的顶部
and is where the fuel and oxidizer mix, hopefully really well, and where the primary combustion occurs.
也是理想情况下燃料和氧化剂混合 进行主要燃烧的地方
截止20200811还没做
可以看看Scott Manley讲喷注器的视频 b23.tv/av925077700
I'll do an in depth video on injectors here soon,
我很快会做一个深入讲解喷注器的视频
but for now, just know in general they mix to a predetermined amount of fuel and oxidizer
但现在 只需知道在一般情况下 喷注器会把燃料和氧化剂按计划数量(比例)进行的混合
which balances performance and heat.
这个比例一般是按照性能和热量进行平衡的结果
The further away from their ideal ratio the fuel and oxidizer are,
燃料和氧化剂距离理想比例越远
the cooler the combustion will be.
燃烧温度越低
Since oxygen is a heavier molecule than most fuels
由于氧气分子比大多数燃料分子都重
and can't be accelerated as quickly as a lighter fuel molecule can,
因此无法像轻的燃料分子一样快地加速
engines tend to run fuel-rich,
所以发动机往往在富燃条件下工作
and they change the ratio in order to control the temperature and performance.
为了控制温度和性能 他们会调整混合比
And in order to locally cool, say,
而为了局部的冷却 也就是说
the outer perimeter of a combustion chamber where the exhaust comes in contact with the chamber walls,
燃烧室的外围 也就是废气与腔室壁接触的地方
you can add a few more fuel injectors
你可以添加更多的喷注器
so there'll be a layer of more fuel rich exhaust that's in contact with the walls.
因此会有一层与燃烧室壁接触的更加富燃的废气层
The most problematic part of a rocket engine is the throat.
火箭发动机的最棘手的部分是喷管喉部
This is where the heat absorbed by the wall of the nozzle is the highest.
这是喷管壁吸收的热量最高的地方
Luckily, this high temperature exhaust is only coming in contact with a small amount of surface area,
幸运的是 这种高温废气只接触很小的一部分表面积
and with a finite amount of cool fuel being pumped through the walls,
并且有一定数量的低温燃料通过喷管壁泵送
having only a small area in contact with the hot exhaust gas is a good thing.
只与热废气接触的区域很小是一件好事
This is backwards from what we normally tend to deal with in life.
这与我们通常在生活中倾向于面对的情况是相反的
If you want to cool something off,
如果你想冷却什么东西
you normally want a big surface area to radiate a lot of heat away like a radiator does in a car,
你通常希望一个大的表面积像汽车里的散热器一样散发出大量的热量
but that's not what's happening here;
但这不是这里发生的事
we have a heat source and it's going to melt whatever it touches.
我们有一个热源 它将融化任何接触到的东西
Think about it like if you had a red hot fire going
想一想 如果你正在烈火中
and you have a garden hose running to try and keep stuff you put in that fire from melting.
并且你有一根花园软管 以防止放入火中的东西融化
Stick a metal rod in there a little,
把金属棒往里放一点
the hose will probably do a fine job in keeping the rod from melting,
软管基本能完全防止金属棒熔化
but if you put more and more of that rod in the fire,
但是如果你把金属棒的更多部分放进火里
eventually the hose will not be able to keep up with the task of keeping the rod from melting.
最终 软管将无法防止金属棒熔化
This is where a larger engine actually has a big advantage over a small engine.
这是大型发动机实际上比小型发动机具有更大优势的地方
The volume of an engine, and therefore the amount of propellant per second in the engine,
发动机的体积 因此对应着每秒推进剂量
goes up by the cube of the engine's radius,
与发动机的半径的立方成正比
but the surface area needed to cool the area only goes up by the radius squared,
但冷却区域所需的表面积仅以半径的平方增加
so larger rocket engines have a lot more propellant to cool only a little more surface area.
因此 大型火箭发动机具有更多的推进剂 来冷却相对少的表面积
Now let's make up some numbers here.
现在 让我们在这里补上一些数据
Say the proportions of the engine are the same,
假设发动机的比例是一样的
but one engine has a throat diameter of 50mm and one has a throat of 100mm.
但一个发动机的喉部直径为50mm 另一个喉部直径为100mm
The engine with the 50mm diameter throat
喉部直径为50mm的发动机
will have an area of 1,963mm² and a circumference of 157mm.
面积为1963mm² 周长为157mm
The engine with a 100mm diameter throat
而喉部直径为100mm的发动机
will have an area of 7,854mm² and a circumference of only 314mm.
面积为7854mm² 周长为314mm
In other words, the 100mm throat engine could flow four times more exhaust
换句话说 喉部直径为100mm的发动机的排气量可增加四倍
while only needing to cool twice as much surface area.
而只需冷却两倍的表面积
But wait, it's still twice as much to cool, right?
别急 它仍然是两倍冷却 对不对？
But guess what, if you're flowing four times as much exhaust through the throat,
但是 如果流经喉部的空气量是原来的四倍
it also means you're flowing four times as much fuel as coolant through those areas as well.
这也意味着你在这些区域流动的作为冷却剂的燃料是原来的四倍
So really, in a sense there's twice as much fuel as coolant to cool a given area
因此 在某种意义上说 冷却给定区域的燃料量是冷却液的两倍
when you double the diameter of your throat.
当喷管喉部直径加倍时
That's a good thing.
这是好事
So a larger engine actually gets easier and easier to cool.
因此 更大的发动机实际上变得越来越容易冷却
But of course, they start to bring on their own problems,
但是 当然 他们也有自己的问题
such as combustion instability,
如燃烧不稳定
but in general a bigger engine is easier to cool.
但总的来说 更大的发动机更容易冷却
And right here is the biggest problem with aerospikes.
而这是气尖发动机最大的问题
By design, the throat of their combustion chamber has substantially more surface area to cool.
通过设计 燃烧室的喉部基本上具有更大的表面积可以冷却
For a toroidal aerospike, the combustion chamber basically has a giant plug in the middle of it
而环形气尖 基本上是 燃烧室的中间有一个巨大的塞子
which greatly increases the surface area of what needs to be cooled.
这大大增加了需要冷却的部分的表面积
Let's do some simple math based on those last chambers.
让我们根据这些最后提到的燃烧室进行一些简单的数学运算
Let's pretend we're trying to keep the same throat area of 7854mm²
我们假设喉部的面积保持在7854mm²的面积
that we had with that 100mm diameter throat.
也就是与直径100mm的喉部相同
Well in order to get that same throat area,
那么 为了获得同样的喉部面积
we'd have to have say a 141mm outer diameter throat and then a 100mm inner diameter plug.
假设需要一个141mm外径的喉部加上100mm内径的塞子
This means we now have more than doubled the amount of surface area we need to cool.
这意味着我们现在需要冷却的表面积增加了一倍以上
We went from having a circumference of 314mm to a circumference of
周长会从314mm
both 314mm plus an additional 444mm for the outer diameter for a total of 758mm.
变为314mm再加上444mm的外径 总共达到了758mm
These numbers are a bit arbitrary here
这么计算当然有些随意了
'cause we really could stretch this just about any way we want,
因为只是举例而已
but one thing that you can't overcome is the fact
但有一件事你无法克服
that you're inherently at least doubling the surface area at the exact place
那就是表面积至少是原来的两倍
where it's the hardest to keep cool.
这种发动机也最难保持冷却的
But truth be told,
但说实话
engineers don't often suspend a plug in the middle of a normal combustion chamber;
工程师通常不会在正常的燃烧室中间悬挂塞子(来做环形气尖)
it's more common to make a ring for a combustion chamber.
更常见的做法是做一个环形燃烧室
But even so, a ring still has an inner diameter and an outer diameter that you now have to cool.
但即使如此 一个环仍然有一个内径和一个外径需要冷却
The J-2T was actually a perfect example of this.
实际上J-2T就是一个很好的例子
It took the turbomachinery from a J-2 engine and was put inside a toroidal aerospike engine.
它从一台J-2发动机上取下涡轮泵 并放入一台气尖发动机内
But just look at this picture of the J-2 vs the J-2T.
但只要看看J-2和J-2T对比的这张图片
You can tell just how much substantially bigger the throat is,
你可以看出喉部大了多少
and now we have two throats of that larger diameter just to make up the same throat area as the standard J-2.
现在我们有两个直径更大的喉部 只是为了补齐与标准J-2相同的喉部面积
The math works out to being almost 15 times harder to cool the J-2T than it is to cool a standard J-2.
数学计算出J-2T相对J-2的(散热)难度提高了将近15倍
That's certainly not trivial.
这当然不是小事
And don't forget you have to remove that heat somehow.
而且不要忘记 你必须以某种方式除去这样的热量
If regenerative cooling through the walls isn't enough,
如果通过喷管壁再生冷却还不够的
you have to add more film cooling,
你必须增加更多的气膜冷却
change your overall burn ratio to cool all of the combustion chamber,
改变你的整体燃烧率(混合比)以冷却所有的燃烧室
or maybe use heavier or more expensive metals with higher melting points.
或者可能使用熔点更高的更重或更昂贵的金属
Any and all of these come at the expense of performance.
这些所有的改动都是以牺牲性能为代价的
Although we're still doing research on the combustion dynamics of aerospike engines,
虽然我们仍然在研究气尖发动机的燃烧动力学
but so far they seem to be a few percent less efficient at reacting the propellant in the combustion chambers,
但到目前为止 燃烧室中推进剂进行燃烧的效率似乎低了百分之几
which wastes some other highly cherishable chemical energy that's in the propellant.
浪费了一部分推进剂中非常珍贵的化学能
And of course, it's possible this all could be fixed with more work,
当然 有可能通过更多工作来解决所有这些问题
but it could just be due to some of the many compromises required to make aerospikes actually function period.
但这样的妥协也许是让气尖发动机实际工作所需要的
So really, the other thing that is a limiting factor for aerospikes is weight.
所以说 限制气尖发动机的另一件事是重量
In general, it seems like aerospikes have a much harder time achieving a high thrust-to-weight ratio
在一般情况下 气尖发动机似乎很难实现高的推重比
when compared to their bell nozzle counterparts.
不像钟形喷管那样
This is mostly due to the larger amount of surface area for the combustion chamber or chambers,
这主要是因为燃烧室的表面积更大
the additional plumbing to feed all the chambers,
同时需要为所有的燃烧室提供额外的管路
and the additional support and structures between the spike.
以及尖头之间的额外的支撑结构
Take a look at the xRS-2200 and look at how much stuff there is between the ramps.
看看XRS-2200的两个斜坡之间有多少东西
Although it seems like there'd be less nozzle,
虽然好像会减少喷管的数量
which may be true, there's honestly more of literally about everything else.
但(发动机)除了喷管以外的东西都增加了
Now imagine you had, say, a hydrogen leak in one of these additional tubes, pipes or valves,
现在想象一下 例如 在这些额外的管道或阀门之中存在氢泄漏
which is really common, because hydrogen's really hard to contain.
这是非常常见的 因为氢真的很难储存
There's a substantially more points of failure in an engine like this.
像这样的发动机中会有更多的故障点
And of course weight is extremely important with rockets,
当然重量是火箭中非常重要的因素
and the thrust-to-weight ratio is a really important metric in rocket engines.
而对火箭发动机而言 就是推重比
After all, extra weight directly affects your payload capacity
毕竟 多余的重量会直接影响你的有效载荷能力
and overall performance of the rocket,
还有火箭的整体性能
so a lightweight and powerful engine is always a good thing.
所以重量轻 动力强的发动机始终是一件好事
Another thing that can be difficult to do with aerospikes is how to gimbal or steer them.
使用气尖发动机很难做到的另一件事是如何平衡或操纵它们
Because of the large attachment points to the vehicle,
由于箭体的固定点较大
it can be impractical to try and move the entire spike with thrust vector control.
尝试使用推力矢量控制来移动整个气尖是不切实际的
Although, one good thing is a gimbaled spike will never exceed its own perimeter,
尽管如此 有一件好事是一个摆动的气尖永远不会超过它自己的周长
unlike a nozzle which can run into nearby engines.
不像摆动的喷管会碰到附近的发动机
A common solution for thrust vectoring is to throttle individual chambers to perform differential thrust,
推力矢量的常见解决方案是节流各个燃烧室
by off-putting the thrust, it will induce pitch or yaw to the vehicle.
通过偏离推力 来控制箭体进行俯仰或偏航
Although it's not as effective as steering the entire engine, it is a viable option.
虽然它不像操纵整个发动机为有效 但仍然是一个可行的选择
The RS-2200 linear aerospike was to use both actuated thrust vectoring and throttling.
RS-2200线性气尖发动机将同时使用推力矢量控制和节流
On the pitch and roll axis it had actuated control
在俯仰和滚转轴上 可以使用推力矢量控制
and for yaw control it'd throttle individual chambers all the way down to 18%.
而对于偏航 可以把各个燃烧室的节流阀一直降到18%来进行控制
And the last big deal with aerospikes is actually the lack of real flight data.
最后一个大问题是气尖发动机缺乏真实的飞行数据
Now although this seems like a simple solution,
尽管现在看起来这是个不算难事
or a perfect submission for the "Why Don't They Just" segment
或者是为什么不这样做 部分的完美陈述
on "Our Ludicrous Future Podcast" that I'm the cohost of.
也就是我作为共同主持人的博客我们滑稽的未来 中的一部分
I mean, why don't they just fly an aerospike?
为什么他们不使用一个气尖发动机？
Which by the way
if you don't listen to Our Ludicrous Future podcast here on YouTube
or on your favorite podcast player,
definitely get on that if you want your weekly fill of space news,
Evs, futurism, et cetera, et cetera.
Sorry, shameless plug.
对不起 大言不惭地恰饭
But the thing that hasn't really been proven out is
但是 还没有被证实的是
what happens with aerospikes between supersonic speeds,
超音速下的气尖发动机会发生什么
or above mach one, up to hypersonic speeds of mach five.
或高于一马赫 甚至是高超音速比如五马赫
And this is a non-trivial thing.
这是一个比较复杂的事情
But one really really cool experiment was with the LASRE experiment,
但是LASRE实验是一个非常酷的实验
which was taking a scale mockup of the X-33 tail and aerospike engine, putting it on an SR-71,
当时使用X-33尾翼和气尖发动机的比例模型 并将其安装在SR-71上
and flying above supersonic speeds.
并以超音速飞行
There were actually seven research flights with the LASRE experiment on an SR-71,
实际上 在SR-71上进行了LASRE实验的7次试验飞行
and although they never actually fired the engine,
虽然他们从来没有真正启动发动机
they did perform cold firing tests at Mach 1.58 and ground firings
他们确实在1.58马赫的速度下进行了冷点火试验以及地面点火试验
which gave them all the information necessary to move on.
这给了他们后面继续试验的所有必要信息
But regardless of how cool it looks,
但不管它看起来多么酷
the aerospike engine still lacks any real runtime data in these supersonic and hypersonic regimes
这些超音速飞行的气尖发动机仍然缺少任何超音速和高超音速下的真实飞行数据
or almost any real full scale flight data, period.
或者任何全尺寸的飞行数据
气尖喷管和钟形喷管的对比
Okay I think it's time we actually put up some aerospike engines against more traditional engines
好吧 我想是时候将一些气尖发动机与传统发动机
and see how they compare.
进行对比了
So let's start off with our line up of traditional bell engines.
那么 让我们从我们的传统的钟形喷管发动机开始
For this we're going be looking at original J-2,
为此 我们先看看原本的J-2
the J-2S that was intended to replace the J-2 engine,
以及原本打算用来取代J-2发动机的J-2S
then we'll look at the Space Shuttle's main engine, the RS-25, as well as SpaceX's Raptor engine.
然后我们将看看航天飞机的主发动机RS-25 以及SpaceX的猛禽的发动机
The reason I chose these engines is because they're substantial engines that have a lot of data,
我选择了这些发动机是因为他们是实际生产的发动机 有大量的数据
they're either alternatives to the aerospike, the basis of aerospikes,
它们既可以替代气尖发动机 也可以作为气尖发动机的基础
and/or considered the best engines ever made.
或者被认为是有史以来最好的发动机
This way we get a variety of engines to compare different aerospikes to,
通过这种方式 可以让不同的气尖发动机与不同种类的发动机进行比较
and each of these engines performs in the vacuum of space
这些发动机都可以在真空中发挥作用
or in the case of the RS-25 and the Raptor engine,
或者像RS-25和猛禽一样
they operate in space and at sea level like an aerospike does.
它们同时在海平面和真空中工作 就像气尖发动机一样
Now, for aerospike engines, we really only have three engines
现在 真的就只有三个气尖发动机
that really made it through a legitimate certification and testing program,
通过了正当的认证和测试程序
but only two that I have good hard numbers on,
但只有两个我有确切的数据
and then there's one more engine that would have perhaps been the king of aerospikes.
还有一个发动机可能是气尖发动机之王
So the engines with the most data
因此 拥有最多数据的发动机
that I could find were the J-2T 250K toroidal aerospike and the XRS-2200.
我能找到的是J-2T(250K)环形气尖发动机和XRS-2200
By comparing these engines to the J-2S which it was based off of,
通过将这些发动机与它所基于的J-2S进行比较
we should get a good idea of their performance.
我们应该对他们的表现有所了解
The other aerospike we're going to look at is the RS-2200,
另外一台气尖发动机 我们要看的是RS-2200
which was the full scale engine that would've actually powered the Venture Star.
这就是那个为冒险星 提供动力的全尺寸发动机
Now all of these numbers will have a pretty big asterisk next to them,
那么 所有这些数字旁边都会有一个很大的星号
because this engine never actually hit the test stand
因为这台发动机从未真正进行过试车
and it relied on a lot of new, unproven-ish technologies to get these numbers,
这些数据也是通过未经验证的技术来获得的
such as a lightweight carbon ramps and ceramic tubes.
诸如轻质碳(气尖)坡道和陶瓷管路
So the numbers quoted here are
所以这里引用的数据是
what they would've needed to reach in order to make the Venture Star work,
能让冒险星 成功运行的目的指标
and truth be told, getting an engine to hit your targets can be very, very difficult.
而且说实话 让发动机达到预期目标是很困难的
But the numbers on Raptor are just the current numbers and, just like the Merlin engine,
但是猛禽发动机上的数据就只是当前数据 就像梅林发动机一样
we do expect to see SpaceX continue to push this engine
我们确实希望看到SpaceX继续改进这一发动机
and develop it beyond these numbers in the very near future.
并在不久的将来发展到超过这些(现有)数据
And one more note, I should also point out that all of these engines are drawn to scale of each other.
还有一点 我应该指出的是 所有这些发动机都是按(相同)比例绘制的
So let's start off with each engine's fuel.
因此 让我们从每个发动机的燃料开始
Every engine here runs on liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen otherwise known as hydrolox
每个依靠液氢和液氧工作的发动机叫做氢氧发动机
except the Raptor engine which runs on liquid methane and liquid oxygen, or methalox.
猛禽发动机除外 因为猛禽是依靠液氧和液态甲烷工作的液氧甲烷发动机
I wanted most of the engines to be hydrolox
我觉得大部分(用来对比气尖发动机)的发动机应该是氢氧发动机
so we're comparing the most apples to apples engines
这样才好控制变量
since hydrolox engines have the most potential for a high specific impulse.
因为氢氧发动机的高比冲潜力最好
But it's still fun to compare them here to the methalox Raptor.
但是在这里将它们与液氧甲烷的猛禽进行比较仍然很有趣
Next let's look at their cycles.
接下来让我们看看他们的循环方式
And again, if you need a rundown on engine cycles,
再次说明 如果你需要了解发动机循环方式
b23.tv/av57059171
I go into most of these in my video about the Raptor engine
我在有关猛禽发动机的视频中介绍了其中大多数内容
and its full flow staged combustion cycle.
还有猛禽发动机的全流量补燃循环
But the one engine cycle type
但是 一个发动机循环方式
that I didn't talk about is the tap-off method
我没有说的是 抽气循环
which actually just uses the primary combustion chamber to power the turbine.
这实际上是只使用主燃烧室来驱动涡轮泵
The engine here that uses the tap-off method is the J-2S
此处使用抽气循环的发动机是J-2S
which was intended to help simplify the engine
其目的是帮助简化发动机
and bring the cost down since it eliminated the preburner or gas generator.
并把成本降下来 因为它减少了预燃室或气体发生器
The original J-2, the J-2T 250K, the XRS-2200, and the RS-2200 all use a gas generator.
原版J-2 J-2T(250K)  XRS-2200 和RS-2200都使用的燃气发生器
The RS-25 is closed cycle, fuel rich,
而RS-25是闭式富燃(分级燃烧)循环
and the Raptor engine is of course full flow staged combustion cycle.
以及猛禽发动机当然是全流量补燃循环
Now let's look at their thrust output.
现在让我们来看看他们的推力输出
We'll do both sea-level and vacuum thrust in kilonewtons.
同时对比海平面和真空推力 以千牛顿作为单位
The J-2 produced 486 kN at sea level and 1,033 kN in a vacuum,
J-2海平面推力为486千牛 而真空推力为1033千牛
the J-2S couldn't actually fire at sea level and in space produced 1,138 kN,
J-2S在海平面不能正常工作 而真空推力为1138千牛
the J-2T(250K) produced 731 kN at sea level and it would do 1,112 kN in space,
J-2T(250K)海平面推力为731千牛 而真空推力为1112千牛
the XRS-2200 was 909 kN at sea level and 1,184 kN in space,
XRS-2200海平面推力为909千牛 而真空推力为1184千牛
the RS-2200 would have hopefully produced 1,917 kN at sea level and 2,201 kN in space,
理想情况下 RS-2200海平面推力为1917千牛 而真空推力为2201千牛
the RS-25 produces 1,859 kN at sea level and 2,278 kN in space
RS-25海平面推力为1859千牛 而真空推力为2278千牛
and the Raptor engine produces 1,960 kN at sea level and 2,150 kN in space.
猛禽发动机海平面推力为1960千牛 而真空推力为2150千牛
Now let's look at their efficiency measured in seconds or the engine's specific impulse.
现在 让我们看看以秒为单位的效率 或者说发动机的比冲
You can think of this like the fuel economy of a gas-powered car.
你可以认为这就像一个燃油汽车的燃油经济性
So a high specific impulse would be similar to a high mpg or km/l.
所以 高比冲量将类似于高英里/升或公里/升
The best way to think of specific impulse is imagine you had one kg of propellant.
想象比冲的最好办法是 假设有1kg的推进剂
For how many seconds can the engine push with 9.81 newtons of force?
如果发动机以9.81牛的力进行推进 能推多少秒
The longer it can sip on the fuel while still pushing that hard, the higher its specific impulse,
保持相同推力和燃料的情况下 发动机工作得时间越长 其比冲也就越高
and therefore the more work it can do with the same amount of fuel,
也就意味着相同燃料下其做的工作越多
in other words it's fuel economy.
换句话说 它的燃料经济性
So the higher the specific impulse, the less fuel it takes to do the same amount of work, which is a good thing.
因此 较高的比冲意味着较少的燃料能做同样的工作量 这是一件好事
A fuel efficient engine is extremely important.
燃料高效的发动机是非常重要的
The J-2 was 200 seconds at sea level and 424 seconds in space,
J-2海平面比冲为200秒 而真空比冲为424秒
the J-2S couldn't fire at sea level and was 436 seconds in space,
J-2S不能在海平面工作 而真空比冲为436秒
the J-2T was 290 seconds at sea level and 441 seconds in space,
J-2T海平面比冲为290秒 而真空比冲为441秒
the XRS-2200 was 339 seconds at sea level and 436 in space,
XRS-2200海平面比冲为339秒 而真空比冲为436秒
the RS-2200 was planned to have 347 seconds at sea level and 455 seconds in space,
理想情况下 RS-2200海平面比冲为347秒 而真空比冲为455秒
the RS-25 is 363 at sea level and 453 seconds in space,
RS-25海平面比冲为363秒 而真空比冲为453秒
and the Raptor engine is 330 seconds at sea level and 355 seconds in space.
猛禽发动机海平面比冲为330秒 而真空比冲为355秒
b23.tv/av57059171
Now as we mentioned previously in the video,
那么 正如我们前面那个视频所说的那样
a huge factor in the specific impulse of an engine is the expansion ratio.
发动机的比冲中的一个重要因素是膨胀比
So let's see if there's a strong correlation between expansion ratios and their specific impulse.
因此 让我们看看它们的膨胀比和比冲之间是否存在很强的相关性
The J-2 was 27:1, the J-2S was 40:1,
J-2是27比1，J-2S为40比1
the J-2T was 80:1, the XRS-2200 was 58:1,
J-2T为80比1，XRS-2200为58比1
the RS-2200 would've had a crazy 173:1,
RS-2200能达到疯狂的173比1
the RS-25 is 69:1 and the Raptor is 35:1.
RS-25是69比1 而猛禽是35比1
It should be noted that although the J-2S has a higher expansion ratio,
应当注意的是 虽然J-2S具有较高的膨胀比
it's dimensions look almost identical to the J-2.
它的尺寸看起来和J-2几乎相同
That's on purpose;
这是故意的
it's because the throat diameter is actually smaller on the J-2S
这是因为J-2S的喉部直径实际上比较小
compared to the J-2 in order to increase the expansion ratio
因此 相比J-2才能提高膨胀比
but also to keep the same general dimensions which would make it a drop-in replacement of the J-2.
同时 大体上的尺寸相同 又让其容易替换掉J-2
And lastly, let's look at their thrust-to-weight ratio.
最后 让我们来看看他们的推重比
Now this one we definitely need to remind you
现在 这一块我得提醒你
that these numbers could be off by a little bit
这些数字可能存在一些偏差
as each company might quote the engine with varying amounts of hardware, or have different metrics for this,
因为每个公司描述的发动机可能存在不同数量的设备 或有着不同的指标
but in general, we can use these numbers as a decent rule of thumb.
但在一般情况下 我们可以用这些数字用作合理的经验法则
The J-2 was 73:1, and although the J-2S was simpler with no preburner, it was a little heavier,
J-2为73比1 而虽然J-2S结构更简单 没有预燃室 但是有点重
and had a 69:1 thrust-to-weight ratio,
其推重比为69比1
the J-2T was 63:1, the XRS-2200 was 35:1,
J-2T为63比1 XRS-2200为35比1
the RS-2200 was planning to hit 83:1,
而RS-2200的目标为83比1
but would've needed to hit 75:1 in order to make its SSTO capabilities possible,
但必须要达到75比1 才能做到SSTO
the RS-25 is 73:1 and the Raptor is 107:1.
RS-25是73比1 而猛禽是107比1
So now that we have all of these numbers,
那么 数据总结完毕
we can really see how aerospikes compare to more traditional engines.
我们可以好好看看气尖发动机和传统发动机的对比结果了
And in general, the J-2T and XRS-2200 should be compared to the J-2S
而在一般情况中 J-2T和XRS-2200应当相比于J-2S
since that was really what was meant to replace the J-2.
因为J-2S是为了取代J-2而产生的
And when we do so, we can definitely see why both of these engines were advantageous.
这样我们肯定可以看到为什么这两个发动机都更具优势
They offer great vacuum performance and they can still be used at sea level,
他们提供了极大的真空性能 同时仍可在海平面使用
something the J-2S physically couldn't do.
而J-2S海平面干脆不能工作
And in this case, the J-2T even seems to have been a better choice for an upgrade to the J-2
而在这种情况下 J-2T甚至似乎变成了J-2升级计划中更好的选择
than the J-2S in literally every metric except for thrust-to-weight ratio.
比J-2S几乎所有方面都好 除了推重比稍差
It was really a compelling option.
J-2T确实相当优秀
And now when we compare all of these to the Raptor engine, we can clearly see that
那么 现在我们来让其他发动机对比下猛禽发动机 我们可以清楚地看到
the Raptor engine with a sea level nozzle and methalox isn't nearly as efficient in a vacuum,
使用海平面喷管和液氧甲烷燃料的猛禽发动机在真空方面的效率还差得比较远
but with a mighty impressive thrust-to-weight ratio and solid sea level specific impulse,
但具有令人印象深刻的强大推重比和不错的海平面比冲
it's sort of out there on its own.
(在一群氢氧发动机的对比下)有点特立独群
Now had the RS-2200 actually made it through development and truly hit all of these numbers,
那么 如果RS-2200能完成研发 并达到设计指标
it would've been a very impressive engine.
它也会是一台很优秀的发动机
Not only does it have the best vacuum efficiency,
它不仅有最好的真空效率
it also would've managed to beat the RS-25's thrust-to-weight ratio.
它也已经成功地超过了RS-25的推重比
That being said, I've actually heard from multiple sources that,
话虽这么说 其实我已经从多个来源听说
had Lockheed just simply stuck with the RS-25 for the Venture Star,
如果洛克希德只是单纯的坚持在冒险星 上使用RS-25
it would've been just as good of an option
它仍然会是一个很好的选项
and was already a complete engine compared to the RS-2200
相对于RS-2200 它已经是一个完整的发动机
which would've still had a full risky and costly development ahead.
而RS-2200仍然有一个完整的高风险 高成本的研发过程
But now, with that in mind,
但现在 考虑到这一点
I think it's time we hear from real experts
我认为是时候让我们听听真正的专家们怎么说
who have either worked on aerospikes or who have opted against using them.
也就是曾为气尖发动机工作过 或者选择不要使用它们的人
专家们有什么想法
So I actually reach out to Tory Bruno,
那么 我竟然联系上了Tory Bruno
需要注意的是，X-33时期ULA尚未成立，那时Tory在洛马
the CEO of ULA who actually worked on the X-33 and Venture Star program
他是联合发射联盟的CEO 曾参与X-33和冒险之星项目的工作
to hear what he has to say.
来听听他的意见
"The toughest part about the design and operation "of an aerospike engine is thermal management.
关于气尖发动机设计和运行中最困难的部分 是热量管理
"A traditional aerospike engine is conical in shape and can really struggle with heating as the spike tapers down."
传统的锥形气尖发动机尖端越小 就越难处理加热的问题
"The linear aerospike design, together with the strategy of truncating the taper,"
线性气尖的设计 还有截断锥形的策略
"goes a long way to simplifying this problem, but it is still there."
虽然花了很多功夫来简化这个问题 但它仍然是存在的
I also asked Tory
我还问他
if he thought the RS-2200 engine could have met the metrics it was intended to hit.
他是否认为RS-2200发动机能满足其设计指标
He said: "I'm sure the engine would have worked and been practical."
他说 我敢肯定 发动机会工作 并实际可用
"The complexity of so many separate engines, however,"
尽管这台发动机有着这么多独立发动机的复杂性
"would have presented a weight growth challenge"
这将会带来重量增加的挑战性
"as well as significant propellant flow management complexity."
以及显著的推进剂流量管理复杂性
And I just had to ask him if, after working with aerospikes, if he loved them or hated them.
而我得问他 在做过气尖发动机以后 是喜欢气尖还是讨厌气尖
"I love them."
我喜欢气尖
"Aerospikes are just plain cool,"
气尖就是帅
"and linear aerospikes are the coolest type." I agree Tory.
而线性气尖是最帅的 这点我同意Tory
I also asked Elon Musk why he hasn't opted to use an aerospike engine for anything at SpaceX,
我也问过马一龙为何不选择在SpaceX公司的产品上使用气尖发动机
and here's what he said.
而下面就是他的回答
原视频中字版b23.tv/av70314372
- You know, I've internally asked this question so many times, like, "Guys,"
- 你知道 我已经在内部提出过很多次这个问题 比如 伙计们
"shouldn't we maybe do an aerospike?" You've got to get your combustion efficiency.
我们也许该做个气尖发动机？ 你需要把燃烧室效率
There's really two parts to ...
这确实是两个部分...
When you have a rocket engine, what are you trying to do?
当你有一个火箭发动机时 你想要做什么？
You're trying to shoot things out as fast as possible in a straight line.
你想要把物体尽可能快地通过一条直线的轨迹发射出去
- Yes.
- 是的
Converting as much thermal and pressure into kinetic energy.
将尽可能多的温度和压力转化为动能
- Yes, exactly.
- 对 就是这样
So you have your combustion efficiency.
所以 当燃烧效率比较高的时候
So, what percentage of max theoretical combustion efficiency are you?
换句话说 你的燃烧室的最大理论燃烧效率有多少
And then, what's your nozzle efficiency, which is really ...
然后 （才是）你的喷管效率 这实际上是...
Are you straightening the flow and shooting the molecules out in a straight line
发动机的喷流是否是直线
so that you're going the other direction;
这样 你才能去这个发动机喷流方向的反方向
Newton's Third Law.
牛顿第三定律
- Yup.
- 对
- So ...
- 所以...
With a traditional combustion chamber,
使用传统的燃烧室
you can get to a very high combustion efficiency,
你可以得到一个非常高的燃烧效率
'cause the molecules are all sort of bouncing around in there,
因为（这种设计）可以让分子充分地碰撞
they've got a time to combine and do their thing.
让它们有时间结合在一起完成反应
And then when you sort of choke it through the throat,
比如通过喷管喉部的时候将喷流收窄
that gives them sort of more opportunity to combine.
这让反应更加充分地进行
We think we can probably get to 90, certainly 98.5,
我们认为 我们大概可以达到90% 具体来说是98.5%
hopefully 99% of theoretical combustion efficiency.
希望是99％的理论燃烧效率
This is so, if God himself came and knitted together the molecules,
这个效率之高 以至于就算是上帝亲自来把分子织在一起
you're 1% better, okay, maybe 1.5% better.
最多也就是比这个值高1%或者1.5%
That's very high efficiency.
这是非常高的效率
- Because of full flow stage combustion.
- 这得益于全流量补燃
- Full flow stage combustion, exactly.
- 全流量补燃 没错
You've got a gas-gas interaction.
（这种构型）会有气气相互作用
So you've got two hot gases combining.
那么 两种热气相互结合
- Yeah.
- 没错
- And with a relatively simple reaction.
- 只会进行相对简单的反应
Only thing that would be simpler would be hydrogen.
更简单的事情就是氢了（氢氧燃料）
You actually want to say,
实际上 如果你想问
what is the actual achievable combustion efficiency times the theoretical chemical energy?
实际可达到的燃烧效率乘以理论化学能是多少？
That's the real number.
这才是真正的数字
- Right.
- 对
- This is where methane starts to look really good.
- 也就是这里 甲烷的数据才开始看起来变得非常好
这期访谈视频出来的时候，气尖发动机的视频还没出来，所以是剧透
- And so you don't think-- You're just telling me now, spoiler alert,
- 所以你不觉得 或者你现在就告诉我 （剧透警告）
you're probably never gonna see a full flow stage combustion cycle aerospike engine produced by SpaceX?
你可能永远不会看到SpaceX生产的全流量补燃循环的气尖发动机了？
- You know ...
- 你知道的...
If somebody can show that we're wrong, that would be great.
如果有人能证明我们错了 那很好
- Yeah.
- 没错
- If somebody can explain, like, "Wow, there is a way to make your design better," this is a gift.
- 如果有人可以说明 哇 有一种方法 可以使你的设计更好 这就是天才
- Right.
- 对
- I would be like, "Thank you for this great gift.
- 我会这么说 感谢天才
"Wow, this is awesome." It's definitely ...
哇 这太棒了 这绝对是...
The worst thing would be like we was to do this dumb design and stick with our dumb design.
最糟糕的事情类似于我们要完成这个愚蠢的设计 而且要对此坚持下去
That would be insane.
这将是疯狂的
- Right.
- 对
Obviously.
明显
- I would love it if somebody could show how an aerospike is the smart move,
- 我愿意看到有人能证明气尖发动机是一个聪明的方案
in which was we will just do an aerospike.
这样的话我们也会跟进做一个出来
- Yeah, you'll just do an aerospike.
- 好的 那时你会做一个气尖发动机的
Aerospikes, with Elon Musk.
马一龙的气尖发动机
(chuckling)
(笑)
So to summarize what Elon was saying,
所以总结一下马一龙说的话
clearly him and his team are focusing first and foremost on combustion efficiency over other things like,
显然他和他的团队首先专注于燃烧效率 而非其他方面
say, an altitude compensating nozzle.
比如 一个可以补偿高度（损失）的喷管
And the other person that I think has some cool expertise on the subject is Peter Beck,
至于其他在这方面有专业能力的则是Peter Beck
the CEO and co-founder of Rocket Lab.
他是火箭实验室的CEO 也是创始人之一
'Cause not only has Peter built aerospikes himself,
因为Peter不仅自己造过气尖发动机
but he has a great view of why a company like Rocket Lab hasn't pursued them.
但同时也很好地说明了为什么火箭实验室这种公司不会使用它
youtu.be/Nj9BncsgvuQ
Why not aerospikes?
为啥不用气尖发动机呢？
Why haven't aerospikes been flown?
为啥没飞过气尖发动机呢？
Did you view them, or did you look at them?
你是否考虑过呢？
Is it something you would love to do at some point, or what?
你是否在某时考虑过这个方案 或者是别的什么情况吗？
Tell me the actual rocket builders-- - The curse of the aerospike.
告诉我实际建造遇到的（困难）- 这就是气尖发动机的诅咒
- Yes! - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 对  - 没错
- Where's our aerospike?
- 气尖哪里去了
- I've got an engine down there that's an aerospike.
- 我以前造过气尖发动机
I mean, I've done my time on aerospikes myself.
我是指 我在气尖发动机上花时间研究过
- Really? - Yeah.
- 真的吗？ - 是啊
I mean ...
我是指...
I guess they're attractive for all of the right physics reasons.
我觉得气尖发动机是有一定的物理学意义上的吸引力
But a pain in (bleep) for all of the engineering reasons.
但是在工程学上属实让人〇〇疼
And it kinda cancels itself out.
它有点像是自己否定自己
I mean, if physics says it's better,
我是指 如果物理学认为这是更好的
but engineering and trying to engineer them,
但是在工程学的角度
it's far more complicated.
就变得复杂了许多
And the mess and complexity you end up driving into them,
而且一旦深入这其中 就会很复杂
and this is my personal experience, driving into them,
这是我个人的经验
versus just a typical conical bell,
相比于典型的锥形的钟形的喷管而言
it's just not worth it.
它就是不值得
- So you physically are adding mass to potentially gain a little bit of--
- 那么 你实际上就是为了性能的一点提升而增重
- You end up at the same point.
- （虽然两种路线不同）但最后（的性能）是一样的
In my experience, you end up exactly in the same point,
根据我的经验 最后（性能）甚至是完全一样
except with a much more complicated system that's unproven.
而气尖发动机这边甚至是一个更复杂的没被验证过的系统
- And I think cooling has always been a big issue because you're just ...
- 我想散热一直是一个大问题 因为你只是...
It's really hard to do that in the middle of a ...
这真的很难做 在尾焰的中间...
(chuckles)
(笑)
in the middle of it.
在（热量）的中间
- Then it's other things like TVC.
- 然后 还有像是矢量推进控制
It's very easy to gimbal a chamber.
（传统）燃烧室是很容易摆动的
Piece of cake.
小菜一碟
But a whole aerospike, do you gimbal the whole aerospike,
但对于整个气尖发动机 你能摆动整个气尖吗？
or do you have a multiple pore aerospike where you just throttle the aerospike?
或者是对于有多个喷注器的气尖发动机而言 你只摆动气尖的部分吗？
And then what about all the altitude compensation effects that you get?
然后 你得到的海拔高度补偿程度有多少呢？
I mean, you have the same kind of complexities with multiple engines, the plume-plume interactions.
我是指 你有着和多发动机一样的复杂度 包括羽流效应
As your ascending through atmosphere,
当你上升 通过大气层时
you've got all those plume-plume interactions and the plumes are changing.
（多发动机的）羽流效应甚至还在变化
And then your control system's changing as well,
然后你的控制系统也得跟着变
because the TVC works ...
因为矢量推进系统的作用...
Functions differently at different plume-plume interactions and recirculation zones.
在不同的羽流效应和回流区中 （矢量推进系统）需要有不同的表现
It's all a pain in the (beep).
这实在是〇〇疼
But it's still less of a pain in the (beep)
但它仍然是一个痛苦少的〇〇疼
than something like an aerospike, in my opinion.
我个人认为 （多发动机）还是比气尖发动机简单的
And the other thing to think about is that if we were a lab, maybe that's ...
还有就是别的东西也要考虑 如果我们是一个实验室 也许这是...
a pure research lab, it's a different story.
一个纯粹的研究实验室 那么故事也许就会不同
We're a commercial company.
（但是）我们是一家商业公司
R&D is ...
研发方面的话...
It's not fun anymore.
就不再是一个有趣的东西了
R&D is just expensive and time-consuming.
研发（对我们而言）仅仅是昂贵且耗时的
So, you know, pick your battles.
所以 你知道 要做好你的选择
- And while I was sitting there chatting with Peter,
- 虽然我坐在那里与Peter聊天
it made me realize that the Electron uses nine engines,
我才意识到 电子火箭使用9个发动机
and I wondered if they could do anything like gimbaling inwards to utilize some sort of aerospike-like effects.
我想 他们是不是也可以通过发动机的向内摆动来利用一些类似气尖发动机的效应
Here's his response.
下面是他的回答
Even if all your engines are able to thrust vector control,
即使所有的发动机都能够推力矢量控制
is it advantageous to actually aim them into the center at near MECO
那么在接近一二级分离的时候 让它们一起朝中心指向 是否是有好处的呢？
or anything as they get closer to the vacuum of space,
或者在任何可能接近真空的时候
or does that not really ...
或者其实没啥用...
- Oh, there's stuff you can do.
- 哦 你当然可以这么做
(laughing)
(笑)
- I may have just figured some stuff out!
- 我也许搞清楚了
Interesting.
有趣
So there might actually be something there.
因此 有可能已经进行过类似的尝试了
I mean, I've heard that the Falcon 9 does something like that too.
我是指 我听说猎鹰9号也做过这样的事情
It's pretty cool that those companies are able to use multiple engines to do kind of an aerospike-like effect.
这是很酷的 这些企业都能够使用多个发动机来实现类似气尖发动机的效应
But perhaps the best summary of the aerospike engine comes from Vector Aerospace
但也许气尖发动机的最好概括来自矢量航天
who worked on several aerospike engines,
他们曾做过一些气尖发动机
including one of their first engines in April 2002
包括他们在2002年4月做的第一台发动机
which was test fired in front of Elon Musk and Tom Mueller of SpaceX.
这可是在SpaceX的马一龙和Tom Mueller之前进行的火箭发动机试车
The engine unfortunately only lasted 200 milliseconds
发动机很不幸地仅仅持续了200毫秒
before it blew the graphite plug right off the injector face.
之后它炸掉了喷注器表面的石墨塞子
But this wasn't their last attempt.
但是 这不是他们的最后一次尝试
They continued to pursue different aerospieks
他们仍在追求着各种不同的气尖发动机
including a 10-chamber, 1,300-pound thrust aerospike engine
包括10燃烧室 590kg推力的气尖发动机
which also unfortunately failed on it's 2009 flight test.
也不幸地在2009年的飞行试验中失败了
In 2016, Vector released this statement,
在2016年 矢量发布这一声明
which I honestly think summarizes aerospikes perfectly.
实话说 我觉得这对气尖发动机总结得很精辟
"While aerospike engines can provide performance advantages,
虽然气尖发动机能够提供性能的提升
"the larger number of parts and components means
但是更多的零件数量意味着
that they are usually heavier than their regular bell-nozzle counterparts
会比它们的竞争对手钟形喷管要更重
"in terms of thrust-to-weight and, more importantly, require very high component reliability."
对于推重比 以及更重要的可靠性都要求更高
So the general consensus I've gotten from people who have worked on aerospikes
因此 我从大多数做过气尖发动机的人们那里得到的共识是
is it's just not worth it.
就是不值得去做它
Not only is the development and research costly and risky,
不仅是研发的成本和风险
but the net gain might not be any better than a more conventional tried-and-true bell engine.
但净收益可能不会比更传统的 而且经验证过的钟形发动机更好
And this is echoed when you learn about Firefly aerospace
当你了解了萤火虫航天时 也会得到同样的反馈
who had a really promising aerospike engine known as the FRE-2
他们曾研制出一个相当有希望的气尖发动机FRE-2
which was to be a 12-nozzle methane-powered toroidal aerospike
这是一个12个喷嘴的甲烷动力的环形气尖发动机
that was to power their Firefly Alpha.
这将用来作为他们的萤火虫Alpha火箭的发动机
After a company reset, the aerospike plans died
在公司重启以后 气尖发动机的计划被放弃了
and now the company is planning to utilize a traditional bell nozzle as well.
而现在公司也正在计划使用传统的钟形喷管
What's going on?
这是怎么回事？
Where are our aerospike engines?
气尖发动机哪里去了？
So how many companies are currently working on aerospikes as we speak?
那么现在还在做气尖发动机的公司还有哪些？
So far as I can tell, one-ish, kind of.
到目前为止 我所知道的 差不多大概也就那么一个
Well, maybe two.
好吧 也许两个
ARCA has a pretty intriguing video series called "Flight of the Aerospike"
ARCA有一个非常耐人寻味的视频系列被称为气尖发动机的飞行
and they are promising to make a low-cost and simple SSTO aerospike rocket.
他们希望做一个低成本且简单的单级入轨使用气尖发动机的火箭
But oddly enough, the latest video in the "flight of the Aerospike" series shows
但奇怪的是 在这个气尖发动机的飞行 系列的最新视频里表明
the company testing their brand-new systems using a traditional bell nozzle
该公司在测试一个使用传统的钟形喷管的全新系统
and simplifying their rocket to running on steam.
并把他们的火箭简化到使用蒸汽运行
Now I want this company to succeed and I really want them to fire off their linear aerospike,
那么 我希望这家公司能成功 希望他们的线性气尖发动机能点火
but from what I can tell,
但（目前）我可以说的是
they've got a very, very long way to go before they would ever be close to flying one.
他们离试飞还差得远
And although the company has been around for 20 years and has yet to fire an aerospike,
而且尽管这个公司已经建立了近20年 但还没点火过任何一个气尖发动机
perhaps they'll make some progress and get anything flying someday.
或许他们会取得一些进展 终有一天能飞上天
But I'm starting to think this too will fall into the
但是 我也开始觉得这也将落入
"well, it turns out it wasn't worth it" category.
好吧 事实证明这并不值得 的范畴当中
The other company that's working on an aerospike is RocketStar, who is pursuing an aerospike,
另外一家在做气尖发动机的公司是RocketStar
but so far their engines seem to be only in the high-powered model rocket category,
但到目前为止 他们的发动机似乎只用在大推力模型火箭的范畴中
although they do have plans for a Starlord rocket which would use an aerospike,
尽管他们确实有计划制造一个使用气尖发动机的火箭叫Starlord
but this is very much a paper rocket so far as I can tell.
但目前来看这只是一个图纸火箭
But aerospikes still have some promise, right?
但是气尖发动机还是有点前景的吧？
I mean, most of the concepts we looked at utilized the open cycle or gas generator engines.
我是指 我们看到的大多数概念使用的都是开式循坏或者说燃气发生器循环的发动机
Couldn't there be ways to improve upon aerospikes that would make them more worth it?
难道就没别的方法来改进气尖发动机 使其更有价值了吗
气尖发动机的未来
There's two pretty promising ideas or technologies
有两种相当有前途的想法或者说技术
that might actually help aerospikes find their place on the bottom end of an orbital rocket,
这实际上可能帮助气尖发动机实用化 并搭载在轨道级火箭上面
the first being 3D printing.
第一个是3D打印
3D printing allows for advanced designs
3D打印允许进行高级设计
that can help make cooling channels and combustion chamber shapes
这些高级设计可以帮助冷却特殊形状的管道和燃烧室
that would normally be physically impossible to manufacture
而这种形状在传统工艺中是无法制作出来的
super easier to manufacture just by pushing a button.
但是在3D打印中只需要按下一个按钮这么简单
There's companies like Amaero,
比如像Amaero这样的公司
I think that's how you say it,
我猜是这么读的
who have built additively manufactured aerospikes out of Hasteloy X
这家公司用3D打印的技术通过Hasteloy X材料制造出了气尖发动机
which is a high-strength, nickel-based superalloy.
这种材料是一种高强度的镍基高温合金
It's really cool to see how they can print these crazy shapes that are required for aerospikes.
这真的很酷 看看他们是如何用3D打印制造出这些气尖发动机所需要使用的疯狂的形状
The other concept that very well might work hand-in-hand with 3D printing
另一个可能与3D打印紧密相关的工作
is a dual expander cycle aerospike engine,
是双膨胀循气尖发动机
and one in particular is known as the Dual Expander Aerospike Nozzle or DEAN.
其中一种被称为双膨胀气尖喷管或者简称DEAN
What's cool about DEAN is it takes the biggest problem of aerospikes, which is heat,
DEAN最厉害的地方在于 它解决了气尖发动机的最大问题 也就是热量
and makes use of it in the expander cycle.
而且在膨胀循环中利用这种热量
The expander cycle is where a rocket engine takes the liquid fuel that cools the chamber,
膨胀循环是指 火箭发动机使用冷却燃烧室的液体燃料
heats it up to the point of phase change,
将其加热到相变点
turning it into hot gaseous fuel and then using that to spin the turbine which then will power the engine.
使之变为气体燃料 带动驱动引擎的涡轮泵旋转
The problem with the expander cycle is actually the opposite of aerospikes.
与膨胀循环相关的问题恰好是气尖发动机的反面
They have a thrust output limited based on
膨胀循环的推力输出受限于
how much liquid fuel an engine can actually heat up and turn into gaseous fuel.
发动机有多少液体燃料能被加热并转化为气体燃料
So, due to the square-cube law, you eventually run out of surface area to heat up the fuel.
因此 由于平方立方定律  (随着发动机规模变大) 你最终没有足够的表面积来加热燃料
The theoretical limit is approximately 300 kN of thrust
理论极限约为300kN的推力
before the surface area to volume of fuel ratio gets to the point
超过这个极限 (用于加热燃料的)表面积与燃料流量的体积的比(产生的能量)
where you can no longer power the pumps adequately.
就达到了无法驱动泵的程度了
But by having more surface area to heat up fuel,
但通过拥有更大的表面积来加热燃料
like an aerospike engine inherently has,
比如气尖发动机本身带来的性质
you can actually get away with a more powerful engine,
你其实可以突破这个限制 造出更强大的发动机
which might be a cool trick for future aerospike engines.
这也许是未来气尖发动机的研制方向
But to date, the DEAN concept has only existed in theoretical papers
但迄今为止 DEAN的概念只存在于理论上
which targets an engine with 111 kN, 383 seconds of impulse in a vacuum and a thrust-to-weight ratio of 108,
概念中的发动机推力为111kN 真空比冲为383秒 推重比为108
which I should note,
而我应该注意到的是
these specific impulse and thrust-to-weight ratios put it on par with the Raptor engine.
这种比冲和推重比于猛禽发动机不相上下
But again, research papers and actual working hardware are very, very different things,
但同样 研究论文和实际工作的设备是非常 非常不同的事情
which is why many of these concepts are studied only in research labs
这就是为什么许多这些概念只在研究实验室中研究
and often don't make it much further nor do they end up being commercially viable, for now.
至少现在是 没能让它更进一步或者商业化
总结
Okay, wow.
好了 哇
You're still here with me.
你居然一路看到了这儿
This ended up being a lot longer video than I would've ever imagined.
这个视频超乎预料地长
So let's do a quick summary.
因此 让我们做一个简单的总结
Aerospikes.
气尖发动机
Super cool on paper,
纸面上很强
a super tantalizing concept that seems to beckon even the most astute rocket engineers,
一个超级诱人的概念 似乎能吸引到最精明的火箭工程师
perfect for your SSTO concepts
对于SSTO概念而言非常完美
that might also need to be reconsidered,
但也许还要重新考虑下
and likely to drain your bank account and make you age a few decades trying to develop it.
而且可能会耗费大量的时间金钱去研发它
But ..
但是..
But ...
但是...
they are super cool
它们实在太帅了
and as manufacturing and material sciences advance,
而随着制造和材料科学的进步
perhaps we'll see companies able to utilize and exploit their advantages and close the gap on the bell nozzle
也许我们以后会看到有公司能够充分利用它们的优势 并缩小与钟形喷管的差距
which has dominated the aerospace industry.
结束钟形喷管目前统治航天业的局面
But perhaps the biggest reason
但是
why we generally don't see too many aerospikes popping up in modern times is simple.
为什么现在很少出现气尖发动机的最主要原因也许是简单的
If they truly offered a clear performance advantage,
如果气尖发动机真的能提供很显著的性能优势
I would assume everyone would be developing them,
我会觉得所有人都会去研发它们
but the fact of the matter is,
但事实是
they kind of wind up right back in the same place as a normal rocket engine.
它们有点退步回到和原先普通发动机一样性能的位置
Now you could probably say the exact same thing about SpaceX's Raptor engine
现在 你也许会说SpaceX的猛禽发动机也是类似的存在
which utilizes a full flow staged combustion cycle.
其使用全流量补燃循环
That was considered far too difficult to really ever be worth it previously.
这之前被认为是过于复杂 不值得去实现的技术
And that rocket engine is extremely complex and unbelievably hard and expensive to develop.
这种火箭发动机非常复杂 开发起来极度困难且昂贵
But the thing is, the full flow staged combustion cycle
但事实是 全流量补燃循环
is just physically the best way to extract all your energy from your propellant.
不过是物理上利用推进剂的最佳方式
I mean, they actually perform better in virtually all metrics than other rocket engines, period.
我是指 比起任何其他火箭发动机 他们各方面的表现几乎都要更好一些
Whereas the aerospike might gain some advantages in, say, altitude compensation,
而气尖发动机可能在某些方面具有优势 比如 高度补偿
but it lacks advantages in other areas which puts it right back on par with other engines.
但是在别的方面都不如其他发动机
So as far as where to spend your time and research,
那么 只要一谈到哪些地方是值得花时间研发的
that's why most engineers have pursued things like closed cycle engines, full flow staged combustion cycle,
大多数工程师都会选择发动机的闭式循环(包括)全流量补燃循环
or the path of easiest manufacturing and development like Rocket Lab's electric pump fed engines.
或者像火箭实验室那样最容易研制的电燃料泵发动机
And just another note here while wrap up about aerospikes,
再总结下气尖发动机
youtu.be/Sfc2Jg1gkKA
and this is kind of similar to how I ended my SSTO video.
这就类似于我在SSTO视频的结尾所说的那样
It's not really the aerospikes that suck,
并不是气尖发动机太糟糕了
but it's their application here on Earth that sucks,
而是它们不适合在地球上应用
'cause Earth is kinda just the wrong planet to utilize them.
错在地球 不在气尖发动机
Ironically, if Earth's atmosphere was any thicker,
讽刺地是 如果地球的大气再厚一点
the aerospike would actually become significantly more advantageous,
气尖发动机优势会变得更加显著
even for a multistage rocket.
即使是多级火箭
But with Earth's atmosphere as it is,
但就目前这种地球大气层的性质来说
the bell nozzle is just too close to the same performance,
气尖和钟形喷管的性能 实在是不相上下
making it a much easier and less risky choice in the aerospace industry.
使得航天业会选择风险更低 更容易(制造)的钟形喷管
If it wasn't for their thermally backwards nature,
如果不是气尖发动机的热量劣势
their advantages may actually outweigh their disadvantages,
它们的优势实际上可能超过了它们的缺点
but perhaps their tendency to melt is the biggest reason
但是热量劣势是无法避开的
why we just simply haven't really seen one leave Earth's atmosphere.
也因此没有一个气尖发动机真正入轨
But all in all, I think the best way that I can summarize the Aerospike
但不管怎么说 我认为对气尖发动机最好的总结方式
is to compare it to like the rotary engine seen on cars like the RX-7 and RX-8 and their predecessors.
是拿去和汽车上的转子发动机如RX-7和RX-8以及它们的衍生品作比较
For those of you familiar with car engines,
对于熟悉汽车发动机的人而言
you may know about the rotary engine.
可能会了解转子发动机
They're super simple; there's only three moving parts,
转子发动机很简单 只有三个移动部件
They're small, lightweight and very powerful.
它们较小 较轻 而且功率较大
On paper, the rotary engine really should have been a more popular choice in the automotive world,
在纸面上 转子发动机应该会在汽车的世界中更受欢迎
but in practice, they're a nightmare to cool and lubricate
但实际上 它们难以进行散热和润滑
and have awful fuel economy and poor lifespan and reliability.
而且燃油经济性 寿命和可靠性也比较差
That being said, they've maintained a major cult following,
话虽这么说 已经有不少人狂热地追求转子发动机
and in some aspects, they still are a good choice.
在某些方面 它们仍然是一个不错的选择
People have always argued that
人们一直认为
if there was as much engineering put into the rotary engine as there has been for the piston engine,
如果有尽可能多的工程设计 比如等同于活塞发动机的那种 投入到转子发动机中
maybe the rotary would be about as efficient and reliable as a piston engine.
也许转子发动机能达到活塞发动机的效率和可靠性
And in the same way, sure,
与之相同 没错
maybe the aerospike could improve and be a more viable choice with an increase in research and development.
也许气尖发动机在研发力度增加之后 也会得到改进 成为一个可行的选择
But much like the rotary engine, would it really be worth it?
但也像转子发动机一样 这真的值得吗
Would it really ever truly be better than the alternative?
难道它真的比它的替代品更好吗
The art of rocket engineering is balancing all of your variables,
火箭工程的艺术是平衡所有的变量
not only in performance but also reliability, cost, development risk, manufacturing
不仅是性能 而且还有可靠性 成本 开发风险 制造
and tying them all together to make the right choice for your vehicle.
而把所有方面都进行考虑才是载具的正确选择
So at the end of the day,
那么 总之
an aerospike's biggest advantage is
气尖发动机的最大优点是
being able to fire a vacuum-optimized engine at sea level, but in all reality,
能够在海平面使用的真空优化发动机 但事实是
why do you want to do that?
你为什么要这么做？
Unless you are for whatever reason required to do an SSTO,
除非你是非要做一个SSTO
you really never would need to do this,
你真的永远不会需要这么做
because it's much easier and much more common to just fire a sea-level engine on your first stage
因为更简单更常见的选择是在一级火箭上使用海平面发动机
and a vacuum-optimized engine on your upper stage.
而在上面级使用真空优化发动机
So what do you think?
那么你怎么看？
Do you think aerospikes are just too cool to ignore?
Think we'll ever see one propel a vehicle into orbit?
Or do you just think the bell nozzle is the right choice?
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
And be sure and let me know what other questions you have about aerospike engines, rocket engines,
or rocket science in general.
And be sure and stick around because I have a perpetually growing list of awesome videos,
and I'm trying my hardest to crank them all out.
Special thanks to Charlie Garcia
for chatting with me for hours and hours about aerospikes
and helping me grasp a lot of these technical points.
He's my go-to personal, actual rocket scientist,
and he has an awesome YouTube channel as well,
so definitely check it out and start learning even more in depth with Charlie Garcia.
And I owe a really big thank you to Martian Days on Twitter.
He did those beautiful engine renders,
and he worked really, really hard to make sure they're perfectly in scale with each other.
And of course, owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters.
If you can't tell, I'm constantly tweaking and trying to upgrade my stuff,
so better video, better audio.
I flew myself down to Mississippi to make sure I had the best footage of an aerospike engine.
I just think I'm trying to make the best product possible,
and especially with my Patreons in our Discord channel,
who literally help me piece all the stuff together.
And I owe a special thanks to Ghost Rider,
who helped me dig through literally dozens of research papers.
There's a couple others too, but you guys just keep me sane through all these times,
so I owe the biggest thank you to you guys.
If you want to help contribute or add your own facts
or opinions or just fact-check our stuff as I research it,
go ahead and consider becoming a Patreon supporter,
where you'll gain access to our exclusive Discord,
our exclusive subreddit,
and even exclusive live streams as well but going to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
Thank you, guys.
And of course, while you're online, be sure and check out my web store,
where you can find things like this.
Limited edition aerospike shirt.
We do limited runs of shirts and merchandise these days,
so if you see something in that store that you like,
you better get it right now,
because there's a good chance we'll run out of stock,
and re might not restock it.
So literally like the full flow stage combustion cycle shirt,
every time it's in stock we sell out right away.
So if you see something in stock, you better get it today,
because it might not be there tomorrow.
And don't forget, if you work in the aerospace industry,
I actually give you 25% off all apparel
as my thank you to you for helping inspire me
and also for helping get humans off of this planet.
And definitely be sure and subscribe to Our Ludicrous Future podcast.
That's the podcast that I'm a cohost of,
where each week I give you your rundown on space news.
So if you want more of me and you're like,
"Tim, your videos take months to make," trust me, I know.
If you want to hear more from me,
every single week you can listen
to Our Ludicrous Future right here on YouTube or on you favorite podcast player as well.
Thanks, everybody.
That's gonna do it for me.
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人